"lang" { 
"Language" "korean" 
"Tokens" 
{
"#commentary\tf2-Comment000.wav"   "[Gabe Newell] 팀 포트리스 2의 세계에 오신 것을 환영합니다. 9년 간의 개발 끝에 드디어 기다린 보람이 있는 게임이 탄생했습니다. 코멘터리 노드를 들으려면 공중에 떠 있는 코멘터리 심볼에 조준선을 맞추고 사용하기 키를 누르십시오. 코멘터리 노드를 중지하려면 조준선을 회전하는 노드에 맞추고 사용하기 키를 다시 누르십시오. 어떤 코멘터리 노드에서는 중요한 내용을 설명하기 위해 게임 컨트롤을 제어하기도 합니다. 이런 경우에는 사용하기 키를 다시 누르면 코멘터리가 중지됩니다.  플레이한 후에 소감을 알려주시면 감사하겠습니다. 제 전자 메일 주소는 gaben@valvesoftware.com이고 제가 제일 좋아하는 클래스는 스파이입니다. 감사합니다. 모험을 즐겨 보세요!"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment000.wav"   "[Gabe Newell] Welcome to Team Fortress 2. After nine years in development, hopefully it will have been worth the wait. To listen to a commentary node, put your crosshair over the floating commentary symbol and press your use key. To stop a commentary node, put your crosshair over the rotating node and press the use key again. Some commentary nodes may take control of the game in order to show something to you. In these cases, simply press your use key again to stop the commentary.  Please let me know what you think after you have had a chance to play. I can be reached at gaben@valvesoftware.com, and my favorite class is the spy. Thanks, and have fun!"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment001.wav"   "[Jeremy Stone] 멀티플레이어 게임에서는 대부분 다른 플레이어가 만든 콘텐츠를 플레이하게 됩니다.  이를 강화하기 위해 우리는 플레이어 간의 관계를 촉진시킬 수 있는 기능을 추가했습니다.  
예를 들어, 플레이어를 죽인 킬러의 프리즈캠 샷은 실력이 뛰어난 상대를 쉽게 기억할 수 있게 해줍니다.  원수 기능은 특정 적이 다른 적보다 더 중요한 목표물임을 알려줍니다.  또한 보복 킬을 통해 추가 점수를 얻을 수 있는 기회를 제공함으로써 플레이어 간에 라이벌 관계가 형성되도록 합니다.
"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment001.wav"   "[Jeremy Stone] In multiplayer games, the content players consume is largely generated by other players.  To enhance this, we added features designed to promote relationships between players.  
For example, the freeze-cam shot of a player's killer helps the player remember specific, troublesome opponents.  The nemesis feature adds an additional reminder that certain enemies are more significant than others.  It creates a small negative reinforcement loop by giving players an opportunity to score extra points with a revenge kill.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment002.wav"   "[Laura Dubuk] 맵에는 넘어갈 수 없는 경계가 필요하지만 맵 자체를 내부 공간이나 협소한 계곡으로 한정하지 않는 한 그러한 경계를 통해 갈 수 없는 지역에 대한 시야를 완전히 가릴 수는 없습니다. HL2와 같이 보다 사실적인 타이틀에서는 대개 이러한 경계에 대한 가상의 시각적 설명이 필요합니다. 그러나 스타일리쉬한 팀 포트리스 세계에서는 화려한 인공미가 디자인의 핵심 원칙이기 때문에 이러한 설명을 단순화하거나 아예 무시해도 게임 환경에 영향을 주지 않습니다. 예를 들어, 플레이 테스트를 거친 결과 빈 공간으로 연결되는 낮은 울타리를 설치하는 것만으로 울타리 너머 지역은 관심과 경계 밖의 지역이라는 의미가 무리 없이 전달되었습니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment002.wav"   "[Laura Dubuk] Maps require impassable boundaries, but unless we restrict the environments to either interior spaces or steep canyons, these boundaries can't always block the player's view of the outlying, unreachable area. In our more realistic titles, like HL2, these boundaries often require fictional and visual explanations. In the heavily stylized Team Fortress world, however, conspicuous artificiality is a core design principle and so we can simplify or altogether ignore these explanations without compromising the player experience. Playtesting showed, for instance, that these low fences leading to an empty expanse successfully conveyed the message that the area beyond the fence is uninteresting and out-of-bounds."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment003.wav"   "[Ariel Diaz] 팀 포트리스의 각 클래스는 공격과 수비에서 저마다 특별한 기여를 할 수 있도록 디자인되었으며 통제 지점은 기본적으로 플레이어들의 공격과 수비를 집중시키기 위한 수단입니다. 또한 맵의 다른 지점으로 플레이어를 유도하는 데도 유용합니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment003.wav"   "[Ariel Diaz] Each of the Team Fortress classes was designed to make a unique contribution to attack and defense, and control points are, fundamentally, methods of focusing players' attention on these core offensive and defensive activities. They're also useful for drawing players to different points of the map."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment004.wav"   "[Jeff Lane] 원래 디자인에서는 공격자가 지점에서 제거되면 그 때까지 해당 지점을 장악하기 위한 모든 수고가 무효가 되었습니다. 플레이 테스트 결과 이러한 상황에서는 적 통제 지점 근처의 단독 플레이어가 적군이 배치된 지점을 장악하려고 시도할 경우 얻을 이익이 전혀 없었습니다. 더구나 남은 통제 지점이 하나밖에 없다면 공격 팀이 더 강하다고 해도 장악 시간이 완료될 때까지 최종 지점을 성공적으로 장악하기가 매우 어려웠습니다. 이로 인해 많은 게임이 무승부로 끝났습니다. 그래서 지점에서 공격자가 제거된 후에도 잠시 동안 장악 진행률이 그대로 유지되도록 방식을 바꿨습니다. 이를 통해 원래 디자인의 두 가지 문제를 모두 해결할 수 있었습니다.
"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment004.wav"   "[Jeff Lane] In our original design, once attackers were cleared off a point, they lost any progress they'd made toward capturing the point. Playtests revealed that lone players near an enemy control point had no incentive to try to capture it if any enemies were in the area. Furthermore, once a team was reduced to defending a single control point, the stronger attacking team was often unable to successfully assault the final point for the full capture period, which caused too many games to end in a stalemate. We changed the capture mechanic so that capture progress persists for a while even after the attackers are cleared off the point, and this improvement fixed both of the problems with the original design.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment005.wav"   "[Jim Hughes] 맵상의 경로는 플레이어의 현재 클래스와 맵 상태에 따라 효율성이 달라집니다. 따라서 플레이어는 경로를 선택할 때도 게임에 몰입할 수 있습니다. 수영이 달리기보다 느린 점을 이용하여 특정 경로의 이동 시간을 조절할 수 있었습니다. 스파이는 잠입을 위해 이동 속도 감소를 감수합니다. 파이로는 주 무기가 물속에서 무용지물이기 때문에 물을 피합니다. 적의 수비가 강력한 경우 뒤로 우회하여 습격하려는 클래스에게는 물길의 이동 속도가 느린 것이 전혀 문제가 되지 않을 수 있습니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment005.wav"   "[Jim Hughes] To give players interesting navigation decisions, routes through a map should vary in effectiveness based on the player's current class and the state of the map. Water lets us increase the cost of taking a particular route, because swimming is slower than running. Spies often accept that cost in order to infiltrate undetected. Pyros avoid it because their primary weapon is useless underwater. If the enemy has a strong defense, the increased cost of the water route becomes a worthwhile tradeoff for any class trying to hit the defenders from behind."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment006.wav"   "[Iikka Keranen] 스카이박스 안의 넓은 공간에 사용되는 메모리를 줄이기 위해 3D 스카이박스의 크기는 1/16로 축소 제작되었습니다. 따라서 스카이박스와 플레이어 공간 사이를 이동하는 열차를 처리할 때는 약간의 편법을 사용해야 했습니다. 실제로 두 가지 버전의 이동 열차가 있습니다. 하나는 실제 게임플레이를 위한, 플레이어에게 알맞는 크기의 열차이고 다른 하나는 스카이박스에 있는 작은 열차입니다. 중앙 건물 양쪽에 있는 작은 수리 창고가 이 두 열차가 서로 바뀌는 지점을 가리고 있습니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment006.wav"   "[Iikka Keranen] We build our 3d skyboxes at 1/16th scale to reduce the memory used by the large spaces in them. This means we have to get a little tricky when dealing with trains moving between the skybox and the player space. There are actually two versions of each moving train; A player-scaled one for the actual gameplay space, and a tiny one out in the skybox. The small repair sheds on either side of the middle building disguise the point at which we swap between the two trains."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment007.wav"   "[Andrea Wicklund] 시합은 승패가 갈리는 것이 이상적입니다. 무승부는 사실상 두 팀 모두에게 패배인 셈입니다. 무승부를 피하기 위해 맵 디자이너들은 두 가지 주요 변수를 고려했습니다. 하나는 팀 부활 시간이고 다른 하나는 부활 지점에서 전선까지의 이동 시간입니다. 앞서고 있는 팀은 부활 시간이 단축되고 부활 지점도 가까워집니다. 이는 승부가 결정될 수 있게 이기고 있는 측에 힘을 더 실어주기 위함입니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment007.wav"   "[Andrea Wicklund] Ideally, matches should end in a victory for one team and a loss for the other. Stalemates are essentially a loss for both teams. To avoid stalemates, our map design considers two key variables: team respawn times and travel time from the respawn point to the frontline. The team that's winning gets slightly faster respawn times and more forward respawn points, a positive reinforcement loop that increases the chances for them to push forward and win the game."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment008.wav"   "[Dave RIller] 스나이퍼를 위한 맵의 조건은 광활한 공간, 장거리 시야 확보 가능, 엄폐물의 존재 등입니다.  스나이퍼의 목표물이 된 경우 시야에서 벗어나려면 대체 경로를 찾아야 하지만, 이로 인해 이동 시간이 늘어나는 대가를 치루게 됩니다.  따라서 플레이어는 위험하지만 가까운 길을 택할 것인지 또는 안전하지만 오래 걸리는 길을 택할 것인지를 선택해야 합니다  스나이퍼가 위치한 곳의 반대편에는 대개 비슷한 조건의 장소가 있습니다. 노출된 지역을 통과하는 팀원을 엄호하기 위해 양팀의 스나이퍼가 서로를 견제할 수 있는 것입니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment008.wav"   "[Dave RIller] To accommodate snipers, maps need wide open spaces, long sightlines, and protective cover.  Targets of the Sniper require alternate routes that bypass the Sniper's sightlines, though these usually have an additional cost, such as increased travel time.  This leaves players with a choice:  do they take the more direct, but hazardous route, or the safer yet slower route?  Sniper positions generally also have a corresponding enemy sniper deck, positioned on the other side of the arena, which allows one sniper to counter another, offering cover for teammates in exposed areas."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment009.wav"   "[Bay Raitt] 무승부는 대개 문 근처에서 발생합니다. 양 팀의 수비가 견고하여 먼저 문을 통과하려고 시도하는 팀이 질 확률이 높은 경우가 이에 해당합니다. 이 문제를 해결하기 위해 우리는 적이 주 경로에만 수비를 치중하고 있을 때 활용하기 좋은 대체 경로를 제공하고 있습니다. 물론  대체 경로로 이동할 경우에는 이동 속도가 느려지는 것을 감수해야 합니다. 적이 진입할 수 있는 지점의 수는 지역을 디자인할 때 매우 중요합니다. 적이 여러 곳을 통해 진입할 수 있다면 지역을 사수하기가 매우 어렵기 때문입니다. 단방향 출구도 디자인에 매우 유용합니다. 적이 진입할 수 있는 지점의 수와 아군 공격로의 수를 다르게 할 수 있기 때문입니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment009.wav"   "[Bay Raitt] Stalemates generally occur around doors, where teams have a strong defensive presence on either side of the opening. To help counter this, we provide alternate routes with high travel costs that become more attractive only when the enemy has strong defenses behind the main route. The number of enemy entry points into an area is crucial to its design, since it's extremely hard to hold an area when enemies approach from multiple fronts. This makes one way exits a useful design tool, since they let us uncouple the number of enemy entry points from the number of friendly offensive routes."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment010.wav"   "[Jamaal Bradley] 게임 플레이를 위해서는 때때로 클래스의 이동 속도를 동일하게 맞출 필요가 있습니다. 예를 들어, 이 중앙문 타이머는 액션이 실제로 시작되기 전에 모든 클래스가 맵의 중앙 부분에 도착할 수 있도록 하기 위해 만들었습니다. 플레이 테스트 결과 문이 열리는 즉시 팀이 한 곳에 모여서 대기하는 것이 더 재미있는 것으로 판명되었습니다. 전투에 대한 기대와 무작위로 이동하는 열차라는 두 가지 요소가 결합되어 중앙 통제 지점에 치열한 첫 교전이 발생합니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment010.wav"   "[Jamaal Bradley] For gameplay purposes, we sometimes need to neutralize the speeds of the classes. For instance, these central door timers were created to ensure that all classes could make it to the middle part of the map by the time the action actually starts. Playtesting showed that it was more fun to have the teams waiting as a group as soon as the doors open. The anticipation of battle, combined with the hazardous moving trains, creates a great opening clash for the middle control point."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment011.wav"   "[Matt Boone] 방탄 유리는 통제 지점 주변과 같이 집중적으로 방어되는 지역에서 유용한 디자인 도구입니다. 공격 팀은 적 수비자 및 센트리건의 위치를 파악할 수 있고 수비 팀은 공격자들이 결집하는 것을 확인할 수 있습니다. 공격 팀이 메딕의 불사신 충전을 기다리면서 모이고 있을 경우 수비 팀은 이를 파악하는 것이 매우 중요합니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment011.wav"   "[Matt Boone] Bulletproof glass is a useful design tool in strongly defended areas, such as around control points. It gives the offensive team a chance to see enemy defenders and sentrygun positions, while affording the defensive team a good view of the gathering attackers. This is often crucial for the defense if the offense is waiting for a Medic's invulnerability charge."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment012.wav"   "[Matthew Russell] 공격과 수비 맵에서는 일반적으로 제한 시간이 끝나갈 때 약세에 몰린 공격 팀이 불가능한 일을 시도함으로써 무승부가 발생하게 됩니다. 이를 방지하기 위해 전세가 기울 경우 최대한 빠른 시간 내에 승부가 결정되도록 했습니다. 먼저 짧은 제한 시간으로 시작한 후 공격 팀이 지점 장악에 성공할 때마다 추가 시간을 부여합니다. 이러한 방법을 사용함으로써 라운드가 빠른 속도로 진행되고 긴장감이 계속 팽팽하게 유지됩니다. 라운드 시간이 길면 이러한 긴박감을 줄 수 없습니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment012.wav"   "[Matthew Russell] On Attack/Defend maps, stalemates generally involve a weakly positioned attacking team beating its head against the wall as the timer bleeds out. To avoid this, we encourage likely losses to snowball into actual losses as quickly as possible. We start with a short time limit, and then add time whenever the offensive team succeeds in capturing a point. This way the round plays out in as short a time as possible and keeps the tension high throughout. Long round times aren't conducive to the sense of urgency we want to create."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment013.wav"   "[John Cook] 방어 건물의 높이는 디자인할 때 유용한 특징입니다. 예를 들어, 캡 B 건물은 모든 방향으로부터 방어되어야 합니다. 건물이 높고 모든 방향으로 창이 나 있어 안에서 로켓과 수류탄을 발사할 수 있기 때문에 이 건물은 수비자에게 유리합니다. 또한 몇몇 창에 있는 방탄 유리를 통해 접근 중인 적을 안전하게 확인할 수 있습니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment013.wav"   "[John Cook] Height is a useful feature when designing defensible buildings. For instance, the Cap B building needs to be defended from all directions. The height, and windows on all sides, give defenders in this building an advantage, when launching rockets & grenades from within. Bulletproof glass in some windows lets them safely view approaching enemies."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment014.wav"   "[Jake Nicholson ] 솔져를 위해 우리는 공간을 디자인할 때 높이를 특히 중시했습니다. 솔져는 일반적으로 아래를 향해 쏘는 것을 좋아합니다. 그래야 로켓의 격추 데미지 효과를 최대화할 수 있기 때문입니다. 이 지붕 위에서는 그것이 가능합니다. 또한 지붕은 솔져의 로켓 점프를 통해서만 올라갈 수 있기 때문에 일반적으로 다른 클래스는 접근할 수 없는 지역입니다. 솔져는 로켓 점프의 데미지를 통한 HP 피해와 고지대의 이점을 맞바꾸는 것입니다. 이러한 부작용과 더불어 지붕 위에는 HP를 회복할 수 있는 수단이 없기 때문에 지붕 위에서 공격할 수 있다는 이점이 맵 밸런스를 무너뜨릴 정도는 아닙니다. 솔져가 HP를 회복하려면 아래에 있는 메딕의 도움을 받아야 하기 때문입니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment014.wav"   "[Jake Nicholson ] For Soldiers, we design spaces with specific attention to height. Soldiers generally want to be shooting down at opponents to maximize the effect of their rockets' splash damage. The rooftop here gives them that advantage. It can also only be reached with the soldier's rocket jump, making it generally inaccessible to the other classes. Because of the splash damage from a rocket jump, soldiers have to trade health for the height advantage. This tradeoff, coupled with the lack of health on the roof, lets usmake the rooftop a powerful advantage without unbalancing the map, since soldiers will need to rely on medics down below to keep them healthy."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment015.wav"   "[Dave Riller] 스카웃 클래스를 위해 맵에는 스카웃이 더블 점프를 통해 다른 클래스가 이동할 수 없는 길로 갈 수 있는 열린 공간이 필요합니다.  이 지역에는 스카웃이 다른 클래스의 적보다 높은 위치를 유지하면서 통과할 수 있는 지붕, 바위 등의 요소가 있습니다.  스카웃은 종종 자신의 빠른 속도를 이용하여 후퇴한 후에 HP를 채웁니다. 따라서 HP 회복제를 폐쇄된 좁은 지역에 배치함으로써 스카웃이 자유로운 움직임을 어느 정도 희생할 수밖에 없게 만들었습니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment015.wav"   "[Dave Riller] To accommodate the scout class, maps need open spaces that allow scouts to double jump along paths that the other classes can't navigate.  This area features a variety of rooftops and rocks that a scout can traverse while staying above any non-scout opponents.  Scouts often use their speed advantage to retreat and collect health, so here we force them to adopt some risk by placing the health inside a small, enclosed area, where they sacrifice some freedom of movement."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment016.wav"   "[Matt Boone] 스파이는 상대방을 속임수로 제압하려는 플레이어를 위한 클래스입니다. 고레벨에서는 적 팀에 침투하고 변장 상태로 이동하며 즉사 기술인 백스탭을 사용하여 스나이퍼, 엔지니어, 메딕 등의 주요 적을 해치우는 것이 스파이의 일입니다. 스파이의 투명 클로킹 기술은 두 가지 주요 상황에서 도움이 됩니다. 첫째, 플레이어들이 적에 대한 경계를 늦추지 않고 있으며 모두 비슷한 방향을 바라보고 있는 최전선을 통과할 때 유용합니다. 둘째, 적 지역에서 변장이 탄로난 경우 적군으로부터 탈출할 때 유용합니다. 스파이의 공병은 비어 있는 적 센트리건을 쉽게 파괴할 수 있습니다. 따라서 적 엔지니어는 건물에서 항시 눈을 떼지 말아야 합니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment016.wav"   "[Matt Boone] The Spy is designed for players who want to outsmart their opponents. At a high level, his gameplay flow is to infiltrate the enemy team, move around while disguised, and use his instant-kill backstab to take out key enemies, usually snipers, engineers, and medics. His invisibility cloak is designed to help him in two key situations. The first is in getting past the frontline, where players are most vigilant against enemies and most suspicious of friends not heading in the right direction. The second is in escaping from enemies who have seen through his disguise while he's in enemy territory. His sapper was designed to allow him to easily take out unattended enemy sentryguns, forcing enemy engineers to keep a close eye on their buildings."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment017.wav"   "[Eric Kirchmer] 엔지니어의 AI 제어 센트리건의 강도를 조절하는 것은 팀 포트리스 2에서 가장 어려운 문제 중 하나였습니다. 건이 너무 강력할 경우에는 최고의 실력을 갖춘 플레이어만 이에 대응할 수 있습니다. 건이 너무 약할 경우에는 엔지니어가 실력있는 플레이어를 당해낼 재간이 없습니다. 그리고 아예 센트리건을 만들 이유조차 사라집니다. 해결 방법은 센트리건에 이중적인 특성을 부여하는 것이었습니다. 센트리건은 개방된 적에게는 위협적이지만 엄폐물을 사이를 이동하는 적에게는 효과적이지 못합니다. 따라서 엔지니어는 빠르게 뛰어 통과하려는 적을 차단하는 데는 매우 효과적인 센트리건을 설치하고, 센트리건의 약점을 보완하기 위해 자신의 보조 무기 스킬을 사용해야 합니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment017.wav"   "[Eric Kirchmer] Balancing the strength of the Engineer's AI-controlled sentrygun was one of more difficult design problems in Team Fortress 2. If the gun was too powerful, only the most skilled players would be able to counteract it. If the gun was too weak, the Engineer would have no chance against skilled players, effectively eliminating any reason to build it in the first place. Our solution was to make the sentrygun essentially binary in the sense that it's lethal to opponents who don't take cover, but can't intelligently deal with enemies popping in and out of cover. This forces the Engineer to use his own secondary weapons skill to compensate for the sentrygun's corner weakness, while still making the sentrygun a formidable obstacle for any opponent simply attempting to sprint past it."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment018.wav"   "[Andrew Burke] 스카웃은 목표물을 추적하면서 빠르게 움직일 수 있는 플레이어를 위한 클래스입니다. 다른 전투 클래스는 높은 데미지에 의존하지만 스카웃은 빠른 움직임과 더블 점프 등의 능력을 활용하여 적의 화력을 회피합니다. 스카웃의 전투는 대부분 주 무기인 스캐터건을 이용하여 이루어집니다. 스캐터건은 높은 데미지를 입히지만 넓게 퍼지면서 발사되기 때문에 적에게 근접한 상태에서 발사해야 최대의 효과를 발휘합니다. 적에게 접근해야 하기 때문에 본인이 당할 위험성도 높아집니다. 또한 사격 속도가 느리므로 잠시 멈춰 사격한 후 피하고, 다시 멈춰 사격한 후 피하는 과정을 반복해야 합니다. 이러한 패턴 도중에 적에게 명중당할 가능성이 높아집니다. 마지막으로 스캐터건은 탄약이 적고 재장전 속도가 느리기 때문에 재장전을 위해 전투에서 잠시 물러나야 할 경우가 있습니다. 스카웃은 빠르기 때문에 전투에서 후퇴하는 것 자체는 쉬우나 다시 돌아왔을 때 적은 이미 도망갔을 수도 있습니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment018.wav"   "[Andrew Burke] The Scout is designed for players who are able to rapidly move around while tracking their target. Where other combat classes rely on high amounts of damage, the Scout relies on his high movement speed and double jump ability to dodge enemy fire. Much of his combat style is crafted through the features of his primary weapon, the scattergun. It does a large amount of damage, but has a wide spread that forces him to get close to the enemy for full effect, where he's also at highest risk of being hurt. It has a slow rate of fire that encourages him to pause to fire, then dodge, then pause, and so on, which gives enemies a higher chance to hit him at intervals. Finally, it holds a small clip and a slow reload time to encourage the Scout to pull out of combat to reload, something which he can do easily with his speed, and gives injured enemies a chance to run before the Scout returns."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment019.wav"   "[Dhabih Eng] 솔져는 다양한 움직임과 매우 먼 거리에서도 공격할 수 있는 능력을 갖춘 전투에 최적화된 클래스입니다. 솔져는 전투 상황이 어떻게 변하더라도 결코 당황하지 않으며 가장 긴 사정거리와 센트리건 대항 능력을 가지고 있습니다. 솔져의 주 약점은 주 무기인 로켓탄 발사기에 있습니다. 로켓탄 발사기는 탄약이 적기 때문에 솔져는 언제 재장전할 것인지를 미리 계획해야 합니다. 또한 로켓탄이 비교적 느린 속도로 날아가기 때문에 스카웃과 같이 재빨리 회피할 수 있는 상대방을 먼 거리에서 공격할 때는 비효율적입니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment019.wav"   "[Dhabih Eng] The Soldier is a core combat class featuring versatile movement and terrific long range damage capability. He's designed to be comfortable in almost any combat situation, and to be the best long-range anti-sentrygun class. His main weaknesses are designed into his primary weapon, the rocket launcher. It has a small clip size, which forces the Soldier to carefully manage his reloads, and it fires relatively slow-moving projectiles, making it ineffectual beyond short range against any opponent who dodges well, like the Scout."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment020.wav"   "[Charlie Brown] 스나이퍼 라이플 디자인에도 몇 가지 문제가 있었습니다. 플레이어의 기대를 충족하기 위해 스나이퍼 라이플은 한 방으로 머리를 명중시킴으로써 적을 죽일 수 있어야 했습니다. 반면에 급하게 쏠 때는 그와 같은 효과를 발휘하지 못하도록 해야 했습니다. 그렇지 않으면 능숙한 플레이어가 사용할 경우 가까운 거리에서도 적을 한 방에 죽일 수 있어 스나이퍼의 주된 약점이 사라지기 때문입니다. 이를 해결하기 위해 우리는 스나이퍼가 줌 상태일 때만 나타나는 차징 데미지라는 개념을 구현했습니다. 여기에는 의외로 여러 가지 장점이 있었습니다. 
줌 상태가 아니거나 줌 상태를 얼마 유지하지 못한 상태에서는 데미지가 낮기 때문에 스나이퍼는 즉석에서 급히 쏠 경우 상대방을 죽일 수 없습니다. 차지 시간 때문에 스나이퍼는 적은 데미지를 자주 입히거나 매우 높은 데미지를 가끔 입히는 것 중 하나를 선택해야 합니다. 후자를 선택할 경우 상대방의 협공에 당할 수 있습니다. 차지를 다 채우고 쏠 경우의 높은 데미지는 스나이퍼 특유의 사격, 즉 유리한 위치를 차지하여 천천히 조준하여 사격하는 효과를 살려 줍니다.
"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment020.wav"   "[Charlie Brown] The sniper rifle was another tricky design problem. To meet players' expectations, a sniper rifle has to be able to kill an opponent with a single shot to the head. On the flip side, we need to ensure it can't be snap fired from the hip with the same effect, because then, in the hands of an experienced player, it also becomes the game's most lethal short range weapon, negating the Sniper's primary weakness. To solve this, we implemented a charging damage meter that only appears when the sniper is zoomed. This solution has several beneficial side effects: 
The low damage both while un-zoomed and at the initial zoom ensures that Snipers can't kill opponents with impromptu snap fire. The charge time means Snipers can deal out low damage shots quickly or highly damaging shots at slow intervals, which allows opponents to overwhelm them with a coordinated rush. The high damage at the end of the charge rewards Sniper-esque behaviors, such as locating a decent vantage point and taking very deliberate shots.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment021.wav"   "[Marc Scaparro] 파이로는 근접 전투에 가장 뛰어난 클래스로서 습격 유형의 플레이를 장려하기 위해 디자인되었습니다. 따라서 열린 공간에서는 파이로가 취약하도록 만들었습니다. 파이로 플레이어는 폐쇄된 공간과 통로를 찾아다녀야 합니다. 접근전에서는 파이로가 더욱 강력해지도록 화염 방사기에 상대방의 시야를 흐리게 하는 효과를 추가했습니다. 화염에 휩싸인 적은 불타 죽을 때까지 방향을 잃고 헤맬 수도 있습니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment021.wav"   "[Marc Scaparro] The Pyro is designed to be the best short-range combat class, aimed at encouraging players to adopt an ambush style of play. To achieve this, we made the Pyro vulnerable in the open, which forces players to seek out enclosed areas and doorways. To add to the Pyro's short range lethality, we made the flamethrower effects visually noisy, which helps disorient opponents long enough for the flames to finish them off."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment022.wav"   "[Wade Schin] 데모맨은 가장 다재다능한 전투 클래스로서 강력한 공격과 철저한 수비를 신속하게 전환할 수 있습니다. 데모맨은 게임 내에서 간접 사격 능력을 갖춘 유일한 클래스로 모서리에 있는 센트리건을 처리할 수 있습니다. 또한 점착 폭탄을 사용하여 솔져의 로켓 점프와 비슷한 수류탄 점프 능력을 발휘할 수 있습니다. 점착 폭탄은 적이 통로를 통과하는 것을 막거나 퇴로를 엄호하거나 데모맨이 다른 곳에 있을 때 통제 지점을 방어하는 데 유용합니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment022.wav"   "[Wade Schin] The Demoman is the most versatile combat class, capable of rapidly switching from strong offensive pushes to defensive area denial. He has the only indirect fire capability in the game, allowing him to take out sentryguns around the corner, and his sticky bombs give him a grenade jumping ability similar to that of the Soldier's rocket jumps. His sticky bombs can also prevent enemies from moving through doorways, cover a retreat, and defend control points even when the Demoman is somewhere else."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment023.wav"   "[Keith Huggins] 헤비의 미니건은 넓게 퍼지면서 발사되기 때문에 조준 능력이 떨어지는 플레이어도 이를 이용하여 전투에서 활약할 수 있습니다. 정확히 조준하지 않아도 되는 대신 다른 몇 가지 스킬의 중요성이 더욱 강조되었습니다. 예를 들어, 미니건은 발사하기 전 예열 시간이 필요하고 헤비는 사격 도중 속도가 크게 떨어집니다. 플레이어는 언제 전투가 시작될 것인지, 적이 언제 공격해 올 것인지 예측하는 법을 배워야 합니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment023.wav"   "[Keith Huggins] With its wide field of fire, the Heavy's minigun lets players who don't have great twitch-aiming skills still wade into the thick of combat. To make up for this reduction in the value of the player's aiming skill, we amplified the importance of other skills. For instance, the wind-up time before firing and the heavy's reduced speed while firing force players to learn to anticipate both the start of combat and incoming enemy attacks."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment024.wav"   "[John Morello] 메딕은 메인 보조 클래스입니다. 앞서 디자인했던 보조 클래스들은 여러 가지 문제가 있었습니다. 이들은 보호된 지역에 남아 있기 때문에 스킬이 별로 필요하지 않았고 그러다 보니 게임에서 가장 재미있는 부분에 참여할 수가 없었습니다. 가장 큰 문제는 전장에 나와 있지 않기 때문에 막상 치료가 필요한 플레이어가 있어도 너무 멀어서 치료가 불가능해 별로 유용하지 못했습니다. 팀 포트리스 2의 메딕은 이러한 문제가 발생하지 않도록 디자인되었습니다. 가장 큰 변화는 메딕을 전장 한 가운데 투입하는 것이었습니다. 또한 메딕이 팀원을 치료하는 동안 본인의 안전에도 신경쓸 수 있도록 메디건을 최대한 이용하게 쉽게 만들었습니다. 조준이 거의 필요하지 않기 때문에 메딕은 치료 대상을 따라가는 데만 신경을 쓰면 됩니다. 이때 치료 받는 팀원은 메딕의 안전을 책임져야 합니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment024.wav"   "[John Morello] The Medic is the main support class. Previous support classes we've designed had a variety of problems. They didn't require much skill, because they stayed back in defended areas, which also kept them out of the funnest parts of the game. Worst of all, this meant they weren't even terribly useful because they generally weren't near the players who most needed to be healed. We designed the Team Fortress 2 Medic to solve these problems, primarily by focusing on keeping them right in the thick of battle. Additionally, we designed the medigun to be as easy to use as possible, so that Medics can focus on survival while healing teammates. Virtually no aiming is required, which lets Medics concentrate on following their heal target, who has a huge incentive to keep his Medic benefactor safe."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment025.wav"   "[Aaron Halifax] 메디건 디자인의 주 목표는 메딕과 치료 대상 간에 밀접한 관계가 형성되도록 하는 것이었습니다.  우리는 단지 규모가 큰 팀의 협력 방안을 강구하기 보다는 두 플레이어 간의 밀접한 연결 고리가 어떤 결과를 낳을지 관찰하고 싶었습니다.  메디건의 디자인 덕분에 메딕과 치료 대상은 서로를 충분히 인지하면서 HP의 상태와 상대적인 위치에 따라 전략적인 결정을 신중히 내릴 수 있게 되었습니다.  또한 치료를 받는 데에도 기술이 필요하도록 하여 메딕이 치료 대상을 잘 찾고 놓치지 않는 데 영향을 미치도록 했습니다.  우리가 추구하던 관계가 실제로 잘 형성된 것입니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment025.wav"   "[Aaron Halifax] Our main goal in designing the Medigun was to build a strong relationship between the Medic and his healing target.  We wanted to see what we would get if we focused on creating a tight loop between two players, instead of just thinking about getting the larger team to cooperate.  The Medigun's design ensures that the Medic and his target are extremely conscious of each other, watching their health and relative positions, and making tactical choices carefully.  We wanted there to be skill involved in being a good healing target, so that Medics would seek out and latch onto skilled targets.  This helps foster the relationship we were after."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment026.wav"   "[Jakob Jungels] 불사신 상태는 멀티플레이어 게임에서 긴장감을 더하기 위해 추가되었습니다. 멀티플레이어 게임은 상대적으로 싱글 플레이어 게임에 비해 몰입감이 떨어지기 때문입니다.  메딕과 동료가 불사신 상태가 되면 매우 높은 점수를 얻을 수 있습니다.  이는 적군에게는 엄청난 위기가 됩니다. 이들은 적의 불사신 상태가 해제될 때까지 10초간 어떻게든 버텨야 합니다.  불사신 상태는 적 팀이 무승부를 노리면서 일부러 전투 속도를 늦추고 기지 밖으로 나오지 않을 경우 이를 뚫는 데도 유용합니다.  수비 측이 적극적으로 대응하지 않으면 공격 측은 아무런 방해를 받지 않고 불사신 상태가 되는 데 필요한 에너지를 충전할 수 있습니다.  또한 불사신 상태는 메딕이 묵묵히 팀원을 치료하면서 노릴 수 있는 궁극적인 목표입니다. 이를 위해 우리는 메딕이 더 많이 부상당한 팀원을 치료할수록 더 많은 충전량을 얻을 수 있도록 했습니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment026.wav"   "[Jakob Jungels] Invulnerability adds an element of pacing to the multiplayer experience, which otherwise tends to have fewer emotional highs and lows than a well-crafted single player game.  When an invulnerable Medic & his friend come running in, it's an extreme high point for them.  It's also a rush for the defenders, who know they've just got to hold on for 10 seconds until invulnerability fades.  Invulnerability also sharpens pacing by helping a team push through a defensive stalemate, when the enemy team turtles up and refuses to come out of their base.  Without a lack of defensive skirmishers, it's easier for the offense to build up the invulnerability charge without interruption.  In addition, invulnerability is a great goal for the Medic and rewards him for being an effective healer. We encourage the behavior by adding more charge when the Medic is healing injured teammates than when he's healing ones who are already at full health."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment027.wav"   "[Jeff Lane] 멀티플레이어 커뮤니티는 몇몇 맵에서만 반복적으로 플레이하는 경향이 있습니다.  따라서 거의 아무도 플레이하지 않는 맵을 많이 만드는 것보다는 여러 번 플레이해도 쉽게 질리지 않는 하나의 맵을 만들어 보기로 결정했습니다.  대부분의 멀티플레이어 맵에서는 맵을 다 로드하기도 전에 어떻게 해야 할지를 미리 알 수 있습니다.  그래서 우리는 맵에서 무엇을 해야 할지는 말할 것도 없이 시작 지점과 같은 기본적인 것도 예상할 수 없는 맵을 만들고자 했습니다.  따라서 하이드로 모드는 시작 상태가 무작위로 설정되도록 했습니다.  맵의 각종 지역이 지속적으로 바뀌기 때문에 반복된다는 느낌을 쉽게 받지 않습니다.  반면에 전체가 완전한 원형 구조이므로 팀은 전투에 집중할 수 있고, 지역을 확보하거나 잃을 때마다 희비가 확실하게 갈립니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment027.wav"   "[Jeff Lane] Multiplayer communities tend to focus on a small group of maps, playing them over and over again.  Instead of producing a large number of maps, most of which would go un-played, we decided to try and build a single map with more innate replayability than any we'd built before.  With most multiplayer maps, you know what you'll be doing before the map has even finished loading.  In our case, we wanted a map where you couldn't predict even something as basic as your starting point, let alone what you would be doing when you got there.  Hydro therefore begins with a randomized starting state.  The emphasis on control of constantly shifting territories means the map rarely feels repetitive.  Meanwhile, the explicit round structure keeps teams focused, and provides regular highs and lows as the teams gain and lose territory."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment028.wav"   "[Kerry Davis] 일반 게임은 주로 플레이어의 기록을 전 세계의 모든 플레이어와 비교합니다.  하지만 이러한 기록은 거의 세계 최고 순위에 있는 플레이어들에게나 관심의 대상입니다.  TF2에서는 플레이어의 기록을 자신의 이전 기록과 비교하는 방식이 더 낫다고 판단했습니다. 이는 전 세계 플레이어들에게 순위를 매기는 것이 아니라 각자 자신의 기록을 경신하도록 함으로써 동기를 부여하는 것이 목적입니다. 이러한 시스템에서 초보자는 아직 실력이 뛰어나지는 않지만 점점 좋아지고 있다는 격려와 인정을 받을 수 있습니다. 숙련된 플레이어는 자신의 최고 기록과 현재 기록을 비교함으로써 최고 기록 경신이라는 동기 부여를 얻을 수 있습니다.  개인 기록 시스템은 성과 확인 시스템의 역할을 수행하기도 합니다. 플레이어가 자신이 정말 잘하고 있다고 느낄 때 기록 시스템이 '정말 멋진 활약이었습니다'라는 팝업 메시지를 나타내는 것입니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment028.wav"   "[Kerry Davis] Games usually approach stats by comparing the player to everyone else in the world.  This is only really of interest to those who are near the top.  With TF2 we decided that a better approach might be to compare stats to the player's previous successes, turning them from a worldwide comparative system into a personalized motivational one. The beginning player gets encouragement and acknowledgement that while they're not highly skilled yet, they're getting better all the time. The veterans get to see when they've managed to come close to their previous record, which encourages them beat that record.  The personal stat system also acts as a validation system. When a player feels like they've had a really good run, the stats system pops up and essentially says, 'You're right, that was a great run.'"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment029.wav"   "[Andrea Wicklund] 그래픽이 시각적으로 이해하기 쉽게 표현될수록 게임 요소에 대해 설명할 필요성이 줄어듭니다. 최초 버전의 TF2에서는 그래픽이 매우 사실적이었습니다. 하지만 시간이 흐를수록 이로 인해 많은 문제가 발생했습니다.  플레이어 클래스 간의 차이점을 만족스럽게 표현하기가 어려웠으며  총알 이외의 탄환을 발사하는 무기를 표현하기도 어려웠습니다.  두 개의 대항 세력이 별로 멀지 않은 곳에 서로의 기지를 건설한다는 것도 현실적으로 비논리적이었습니다.  또한 우리가 제작한 다른 게임과도 시각적으로 차별화되지 않았습니다.  스타일리쉬한 세계에서는 이러한 문제가 전혀 발생하지 않았습니다. 거구의 중기병을 왜소한 체구의 스파이 옆에 놓는 것만으로도 플레이어들은 이 둘의 HP와 싸우는 방식이 전혀 틀리다는 것을 바로 이해했습니다.  메딕이 치료 대상에게 치료 광선을 비출 때 빨간색 십자가 기호가 함께 흘러가도록 하자 플레이어들은 그 광선의 효과를 바로 이해했습니다.  두 팀의 기지가 서로 인접해 있는 이유도 가상의 세계관으로 쉽게 설명할 수 있습니다.  마지막으로 TF2 스크린샷은 쉽게 알아차릴 수 있기 때문에 우리가 제작한 다른 게임과 혼동될 염려도 없습니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment029.wav"   "[Andrea Wicklund] The more your art direction can use well-understood visual representations, the less work you have to do to explain your game elements. The earliest version of TF2 had a heavily realistic art direction. As time went on, we found this was causing us a lot of issues.  The differences between our player classes were hard to expose satisfactorily.  Weapons firing anything other than bullets were hard to visualize.  Our maps didn't make a lot of sense in the real world, where two opposing forces rarely build bases within fifty feet of one another.  In addition, the game wasn't visually distinct from our other products.  A stylized world had none of these problems:  Put the massive Heavy next to the pinstripe-suited Spy, and players understand both the numerical health differences between the classes and their very different gameplay styles.  The medic's healing beam was easily understood by playtesters when they saw the floating red plus symbols streaming into the target.  A stylized fiction can easily explain why the team's bases are built right next to each other.  Finally, a TF2 screenshot is easily recognizable, ensuring that no one will confuse it with another of our games."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment030.wav"   "[Moby Francke] 스타일리쉬한 그래픽으로 방향으로 정한 후 우리는 여러 가지 스타일을 실험해 보았습니다. 그리고 결국 1900년대 초 대단한 인기를 끌었던 삽화가인 J.C. Leyendecker의 스타일을 차용했습니다. Leyendecker의 그래픽 스타일은 클래스 식별에 필수적인 깨끗하고 깔끔한 실루엣을 그대로 유지하면서 캐릭터의 미세한 부분을 나타내는 데 매우 적합했습니다. 우리는 일반 맵을 바탕으로 여러 가지 의상을 제작했습니다. 이들은 가까이서 보았을 때도 매우 섬세하게 표현되었으며 플레이어의 시선을 무기 쪽으로 끌기 위해 사용된 색상과도 겹치지 않습니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment030.wav"   "[Moby Francke] Having decided on a stylized art direction, we experimented with a variety of styles before settling on the example of J.C. Leyendecker, an enormously popular illustrator of the early 1900s. Leyendecker's rendering of clothing and material provided a great example of how to add detail to a character while keeping the clean, sharp silhouette shapes that were key to our class identification. We used normal maps to craft folds of clothing, which provided a fine level of detail when seen up close, without detracting from color values meant to draw the player's eyes to the all-important weaponry."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment031.wav"   "[Ariel Diaz] 멀티플레이어 게임의 그래픽에서는 캐릭터가 가장 중요한 부분이므로 캐릭터에 가장 많은 노력을 기울였습니다.  우리는 플레이어가 모델을 보는 것만으로도 알 수 있어야 할 정보를 목록으로 만들어 우선순위를 정했습니다.  그 순서는 다음과 같습니다. 첫째로 소속된 팀, 둘째로 캐릭터 클래스, 셋째로 사용하는 무기입니다.  팀 식별은 각 팀에 전체적인 색상의 톤을 적용함으로써 해결했습니다. 레드 팀에는 따뜻한 느낌의 색상, 블루 팀에는 차가운 느낌의 색상을 사용했습니다.  클래스는 캐릭터의 실루엣을 보면 알 수 있도록 처리했습니다. 클래스마다 독특한 실루엣과 애니메이션의 형태는 모델의 다른 어떤 시각적 세부 묘사보다도 먼 거리 그리고 다양한 조명 아래서의 식별을 용이하게 합니다. 마지막으로 무기는 질감을 통해 강조했습니다. 캐릭터의 가슴에 위치한 무기를 들고 있는 부분이 가장 높은 색 대비를 이루도록 하여 플레이어의 시선을 끌도록 했습니다. 또한 캐릭터의 발 근처에서는 어둡다가 가슴 근처로 오면서 점점 밝아지는 미묘한 명암 변화도 플레이어의 시선이 무기를 향하도록 만들어 줍니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment031.wav"   "[Ariel Diaz] Characters are the most important piece of art in a multiplayer game, so that is where we spent most of our effort.  We developed a read hierarchy for player models, prioritizing the information that players needed to be able to read merely by looking at the model.  Our hierarchy was this: first, what team they're on, second, what class they're playing, and third, what weapon they're wielding.  Team readability was addressed by adopting an overall color palette for each team, picking warm colors for Red and cool colors for Blu.  Class readability was addressed through the character's silhouette. Unique silhouette and animation shapes are more identifiable at far distances, and across a broader range of light levels, than any amount of other visual detail on the model. Finally, the weapon was highlighted through the textures. The areas of highest contrast, which attracts player's eyes, are all focused around the chest area of our character models, right where they hold their weapon. In addition, the subtle gradient from darkness around the character's feet, to the bright areas around the chest, also helps draw the player's eyes to the weapons."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment032.wav"   "[Charlie Brown] 플레이어 클래스는 TF2 게임 플레이의 기본이 되는 내용입니다. 플레이어 클래스가 유용한 디자인 도구인 이유는 무수히 많습니다. 클래스는 특정 분야의 전문가로서 게임 내 다른 클래스와 독특한 조합을 이룹니다. 한 클래스에 질린 플레이어는 다른 클래스로 전환하여 새로운 재미를 찾을 수 있습니다. 또한 여러 개의 클래스를 둠으로써 실력과 원하는 바가 저마다 다른 여러 플레이어의 요구를 충족시킬 수 있으며 초보자와 고수가 함께 즐겁게 플레이할 수 있습니다. 신중한 성격이거나 전략적인 수비를 선호하거나 신나게 뛰어다니기를 좋아하는 플레이어 모두가 자신에게 맞는 클래스를 찾을 수 있습니다. 팀 포트리스 2의 다양한 클래스 디자인 덕분에 게임의 결과는 한 플레이어에 의해 좌우되지 않으며 플레이어의 여러 가지 능력이 게임에서 발휘될 수 있습니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment032.wav"   "[Charlie Brown] Player classes form the backbone of TF2's gameplay. There are a bunch of reasons why they're a useful design tool. A class is a bottled up experience, designed to be unique relative to the other classes in the game. A player who is getting tired of one class can switch to another class and get a fresh experience. They allow us to cater to players with a variety of different skills and desires. Beginning and advanced players can have fun together. Cautious cerebral thinkers, strategic defenders, and twitch firing adrenaline junkies can all find their niche. Team Fortress 2's Class design decisions enable us to have a larger number of player abilities in the game, while still keeping a single player's decisions down to a manageable level."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment033.wav"   "[Robin Walker] 우리는 1999년 E3 게임 쇼에서 TF2를 처음 공개했습니다. 그리고 지금은 벌써 2007년입니다. 이렇게 오래 걸린 이유는 무엇일까요?  간단하게 대답하자면 만족할 만한 성과를 얻기까지 상당히 오랜 시간이 걸렸기 때문입니다.  자세한 대답을 원한다면 먼저 게임 개발 과정을 살펴봐야 합니다.  그리고 무엇이 재미있을지 미리 정확히 아는 것은 불가능하다는 사실을 전제로 이해해야 합니다.  실제로도 게임의 재미는 만들고 난 후에야 확인할 수 있습니다.  아이디어 회의에서 세 개의 아이디어가 나올 경우 그 중에서 무엇이 가장 재미있을지는 아무도 장담할 수 없습니다.  따라서 우리는 가장 재미있는 것을 찾기 위한 반복 프로세스를 개발하는 데 집중했습니다.  이 프로세스는 지속적으로 반복되는 작업으로서 가능한 많은 사람들이 게임을 플레이하는 것을 지켜보며 평가하는 것입니다.  TF2를 개발하는 동안 정말 많은 내용을 시도해 보았습니다. 그 중 일부는 최종 게임에 반영되었지만 대다수는 폐기되었습니다.  예를 들어, 초기 버전의 TF2는 한 명의 플레이어가 전장을 실시간 전략 게임처럼 지켜보면서 명령을 내린다는 개념을 기초로 제작되었습니다.  커맨더라고 할 수 있는 이 플레이어는 구조물 건설과 팀의 전체 전략을 책임지는 역할을 맡았습니다.  하지만 여기에는 디자인상 여러 가지 문제점이 발생했습니다.  예를 들어, 커맨더도 재미를 느끼고 전장에서 그 명령을 수행하는 플레이어도 함께 재미를 느낄 수 있는 게임을 어떻게 만들 수 있는가?  플레이어와 커맨더를 어떻게 동등하게 만들 수 있는가?  커맨더의 실력이 형편없거나 반대로 뛰어난 실력의 커맨더가 형편없는 실력의 팀을 지휘해야 할 경우에는 어떻게 게임이 재미있도록 할 수 있는가?  우리는 이러한 여러가지 문제를 해결하기 위해 수개월간 노력한 끝에 만족스러운 결론을 얻기는 불가능하다고 판단했습니다.  커맨더가 첫 단계부터 수행할 수 있는 각종 심층적인 전략을 추가하다 보니 게임이 전체적으로 너무나 복잡해졌습니다.  결국 우리는 게임에서 커맨더라는 존재를 없애고 개발을 진행한다는 어려운 결정을 내렸습니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment033.wav"   "[Robin Walker] We first showed TF2 at E3 in 1999, and here we are in 2007. So what took us so long?  The short answer is that it took us this long to make something we were happy with.  The long answer requires a look at our development process.  At its core is the assumption that we don't really know ahead of time what will be fun.  We know what has been fun in the past.  But if we've got 3 ideas on the table, we can't say for sure which one will be the most fun.  So, we've focused on developing a repeatable process that will find out.  It's based on a cycle of constant iteration, where evaluation is done by watching as many people play the game as possible.  In developing TF2, we tried out many, many features-a few of which made it to the final product, but most of which were cut.  For example, our initial versions of TF2 were focused on trying to build a game around the concept of a commander, a single player who had a real-time-strategy view of the battlefield.  He was responsible for building structures and providing a unifying strategy for the team.  But there were significant design challenges involved.  For instance, how do we design the game such that the commander can have fun, and at same time ensure that the players down on the ground can have fun?  How do we ensure that the players & the commander value the output of the other?  How do we ensure that the game is still fun if you have a terrible commander, or conversely, if you're a great commander with a terrible team?  We spent many months working on these and other issues, and never reached a point where we were satisfied.  In addition, our game had become overly complex, due to our attempts to add a strategy layer deep enough to warrant the addition of the commander in the first place.  In the end, we made the hard decision to remove him from the game and moved on."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment034.wav"   "[Kelly Thornton] 크리티컬 히트는 원활한 게임 흐름을 위해 추가된 내용 중 하나입니다. 크리티컬 히트 시스템은 플레이어의 최근 성과를 바탕으로 크리티컬 히트 확률을 높임으로써 게임 내의 전세를 조금씩 반영합니다. 간단히 말하자면 전투에서 많은 활약을 할수록 계속적으로 활약할 가능성이 높아집니다. 이로 인해 한 플레이어가 연속으로 서너 명을 죽이는 극적인 순간이 간혹 연출될 수 있습니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment034.wav"   "[Kelly Thornton] Critical hits are one of the features that resulted from our focus on pacing. The critical hit system attempts to slightly influence the highs and lows of the game, by increasing the chance of a critical hit based upon the player's recent performance. In summary, the better you're doing, the more likely you'll continue to do well. This helps create those rare high moments, where a single player goes on a rampage and gets 3 or 4 kills in rapid succession."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment035.wav"   "[Adrian Finol] 팀 포트리스 클래식과 팀 포트리스 2의 큰 차이점 중 하나는 투척용 수류탄이 사라졌다는 것입니다. 
팀 포트리스 클래식에서는 대부분의 클래스가 일반 수류탄과 함께 각 클래스에 해당하는 보조 수류탄을 가지고 다녔습니다.  팀 포트리스 2에서는 각 클래스의 고유한 역할에 집중하다 보니 때로는 일반 수류탄이 해당 클래스의 주 무기보다 더 강력한 무기가 되는 경우가 발생했습니다.  이 때문에 여러 클래스가 거의 비슷한 방식으로 전투를 진행하는 부작용이 생겼습니다.  또한 팀 포트리스 클래식의 맵에서 발생한 몇몇 무승부를 살펴본 결과 과도한 수류탄 사용으로 인해 종종 무승부가 발생한다는 것을 발견했습니다. 특히 두 가지가 문제였습니다. 하나는 플레이어가 혹시 있을지 모를 적을 노려 통로에 수류탄을 반복적으로 투척하는 경우였고, 다른 하나는 죽기 직전의 플레이어가 자신이 죽은 후에도 킬수를 올릴 수 있도록 가지고 있는 수류탄을 연속으로 모두 투척하는 경우였습니다.  일반 수류탄을 없애자 게임이 금세 더 재미있어졌습니다. 특히 보이지 않는 곳에서 날아온 수류탄에 의해 영문도 모르고 자주 죽었던 초보 플레이어들이 이 조치를 반가워했습니다. 조사 결과 클래스 고유 수류탄도 이와 비슷한 문제를 일으켰습니다.  클래스 고유 수류탄을 제거하고 플레이 테스트를 해본 결과 게임이 더욱 재미있어진다는 결론을 얻었습니다.  따라서 일단 투척 수류탄을 없애기로 결정한 후 이로 인해 각 클래스가 어떤 점을 손해보게 되는지 분석했습니다.  특수 수류탄을 사용하지 못하게 됨으로써 몇 가지 유용한 수단을 잃게 된다고 판단되는 클래스에게는 다른 기능을 추가했습니다.
"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment035.wav"   "[Adrian Finol] One of the main changes between Team Fortress Classic and Team Fortress 2 was the removal of thrown grenades. 
Most classes could carry a standard hand grenade along with a secondary grenade, tied more closely to the class.  Team Fortress 2's focus on unique class roles led us to notice that the standard hand grenade was a more powerful combat decider than some of the primary weapons.  This made the classes more similar in combat-not a desired effect.  In addition, when we looked at some of Team Fortress Classic's map stalemates, they often resulted from large amounts of grenade spam. Two cases were particularly problematic:  That of players throwing grenades repeatedly through doorways, hoping to kill any enemies who might be there, and players on the verge of death throwing all their grenades in rapid succession, hoping to get a kill after they die.  Removing standard hand grenades made the game more fun almost immediately, especially for new players who were often confused as to why they died, when a grenade went off at their feet. When we examined the class-specific grenades, we found similar problems.  Eliminating them from playtests gave us yet another boost in making the game more fun.  Once we'd decided on removal, we analyzed each class to see what capabilities might have been lost as a result of the decision.  In some cases we added other capabilities, where we felt a class had lost the ability to make some interesting decisions, related to its special grenade type.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment036.wav"   "[Hamish McKenzie] 프로젝트 막바지에 게임의 다른 부분이 마무리 중일 때 일정을 확인해 보니 아직 몇 가지 애니메이션을 추가할 시간이 남아 있었습니다.  회의 결과 무기별 조롱 애니메이션 추가 등의 여러 가지 아이디어가 나왔습니다.  우리는 해당 기능이 혹시 게임 내 다른 부분과 연관되지 않을지를 고려하여 평가했으며 조롱을 추가하는 것이 가장 좋겠다는 결론을 내렸습니다.  조롱은 킬러 프리즈캠과 어울려서 플레이어 간의 원한 관계를 형성하는 데 도움이 되었습니다.  또한 플레이어가 어떤 각도에서 보더라도 근사한 우리의 새로운 얼굴 애니메이션 기술을 뽐내기에도 적합했습니다. 마지막으로 각 캐릭터의 조롱을 추가함으로써 TF2 캐릭터의 뚜렷한 개성이 애니메이션과 성우의 음성으로 더욱 완벽하게 표현되었습니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment036.wav"   "[Hamish McKenzie] Late in the project, while other parts of the game were being finished up, we found ourselves with some time left over for extra animation.  There were several ideas on the table, including weapon-specific taunt animations.  When evaluating a feature, we look at how many other features it connects to, and taunts were the clear winner.  They play well with the killer freeze-cam, adding to the relationship between the nemesis and his victim.  They gave us a highly visible place to show off our new facial animation technology, allowing the player to examine it from all angles. Finally, TF2's characters have a lot of personality, and taunts were the perfect way to show that personality through animation and voice acting."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment037.wav"   "[Eric Smith] 하프 라이프 2를 위해 우리는 Response Rules라는 시스템을 개발했습니다. 이 시스템은 완벽하게 예상할 수 없는 게임 이벤트에 대한 캐릭터의 대사를 세부적으로 조정할 수 있도록 합니다.  팀 포트리스 2에서는 멀티플레이어 환경에 Response Rules를 처음으로 도입했습니다.  Response Rules 시스템은 단순한 텍스트 파일에 대사를 열거하고 있습니다. 그런 다음 게임에서 텍스트 파일에 정의된 규칙이나 조건이 충족될 경우 게임 코드가 캐릭터의 대사를 내보냅니다. 예를 들어, 플레이어가 무기를 재장전할 때는 재장전에 대한 대사를 하기에 적절한 순간이라는 신호를 Response Rules 시스템에 보냅니다. Response Rules 시스템은 게임 내 다른 상황을 확인한 후에 가장 적절한 재장전 대사를 결정하는 규칙을 따라 대사를 선택합니다.  플레이어의 HP가 낮은 경우엔 재장전시 HP가 꽉 차 있을 때와는 다른 대사를 말합니다.  또한 20초 동안 세 명 이상의 적을 죽인 경우나 물 속에 있는 경우 등 상황에 따라 특별한 대사를 할 수 있습니다.  스크립트 파일에 대사와 규칙이 함께 적용되므로 게임 제작자는 별도의 코드 지원 없이도 게임에 여러 대사를 추가할 수 있습니다.
"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment037.wav"   "[Eric Smith] For Half-Life 2 we developed something called Response Rules, a system that lets us fine-tune the way characters speak lines of dialog in response to game events that are not completely predictable.  In Team Fortress 2, we extended Response Rules to the multiplayer environment for the first time.  The Response Rule system works by listing speech concepts in a simple text file; the game code then makes characters attempt to speak when the rules or conditions defined in the text file are met in the game. For instance, when a player reloads his weapon, this signals the Response Rule system that now would be an appropriate time to speak a line about reloading. The Response Rule system checks the state of the world, and matches it to a set of rules that determine the best line of dialog to use for that speech concept.  If the player's health is low, he may speak a different reloading line than if he is completely healthy.  He could play a special line if he has killed more than two enemies in the last 20 seconds, another set of lines if he's underwater, and so on.  Keeping dialog and rules in script files gives the game's writers the ability to add speech to the game without needing any code support.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment038.wav"   "[Moby Francke] 캐릭터의 렌더링 스타일에 대해 논의할 때 우리는 너무 만화 같은 느낌을 주지 않으면서도 삽화의 분위기나 스타일쉬한 느낌이 나도록 하기로 결정했습니다. 이러한 종류의 렌더링에서 일반적으로 사용되는 것보다 더 부드러운 음영 선이 필요했습니다.  따라서 2D 텍스처를 사용하여 캐릭터의 명암을 정의했고 밝은 부분과 어두운 부분이 만나는 곳에는 따뜻한 느낌의 색상을 추가하여 부드럽게 처리했습니다. 알맞은 음영 모델을 만든 후에는 캐릭터의 실루엣 선을 강조하여 주위의 3D 환경에서 돋보일 수 있도록 만들었습니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment038.wav"   "[Moby Francke] In our early discussions of rendering styles for the characters, we decided we wanted them to have a look that was illustrative or stylized, without going to the extremes of most toon shaders. We wanted softer lines for shading than was typical for this sort of rendering.  So, we used a 2-D texture to define the lighting on the characters, and at the point where light and dark meet, we added a hint of warmth to give it that burst of color at the transition. Once we had achieved the right shading model, we added a rim-term to the characters, so they would have a nice highlight around the edges of their silhouettes, which helps them to stand out from the surrounding 3d world."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment039.wav"   "[Dhabih Eng] 입자 시스템의 목표는 재미있으면서도 시각적으로 흥분되는 효과를 연출하는 것이었습니다. 동시에 게임에서의 의미를 아무도 알 수 없을 만큼 너무 고차원적이지 않아야 했습니다.  일반 매치에서는 화면상 동시에 너무 많은 효과가 발생하여 시각적으로 충돌을 일으킵니다.  따라서 보다 분명하고 간단하도록 효과를 조정했습니다.  게임 플레이에서 중요한 효과는 더욱 눈에 쉽게 띄도록 만들었고 단순한 시각적 즐거움을 위한 효과는 배경에서 간단하게 발생하도록 만들었습니다.  "
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment039.wav"   "[Dhabih Eng] The challenge of the particle system was to create effects that were fun and visually exciting, without being so 'over the top' that no one could read their meaning in the game.  In a typical match, there are so many effects onscreen at the same time, that the biggest danger is visual clutter.  Therefore, the effects were refined to be cleaner and simpler.  Those that were most important for gameplay were made easier to see, while those that were mainly eye-candy were allowed to fall into the background.  "
"#commentary\tf2-Comment040.wav"   "[Robin Walker] 9개의 클래스와 수많은 무기 및 고유 능력이 게임 내에 구현되어 있기 때문에 가장 큰 문제 중 하나는 플레이어들이 이 모든 조합을 어려움 없이 받아들일 수 있도록 하는 것이었습니다.  맵 목표, 아군에 대한 정보, 누가 어떤 무기로 아군을 공격 중인지 등에 대한 필수적인 정보를 나열하는 것만으로도 정보의 양이 엄청나게 많아졌습니다.  이 모든 정보를 시각적으로 표현할 수 있는 수단은 없었습니다. 따라서 우선 재미를 위해 모든 플레이어가 알아야 하는 필수적인 정보의 우선 순위를 정했습니다.  맵 배치와 같이 게임을 플레이하면서 알 수 있는 정보는 중요도가 낮습니다. 하지만 메딕의 불사신 충전과 같이 따로 설명하지 않으면 알 수 없는 정보도 있습니다.  2D 요소를 HUD에 추가하는 것은 가능한 한 피하려고 했습니다. 플레이어들에게 몇 가지 추상적인 표현보다는 우리가 만든 3D 세계를 보여 주고 싶었기 때문입니다.  예를 들어, 플레이어의 눈에는 자기 팀의 스파이가 항상 같은 모습으로 보입니다. 하지만 스파이가 다른 팀으로 변장했을 경우 그것을 알 수 있어야 합니다.  그래서 스파이의 머리 위에 현재의 변장을 나타내는 아이콘을 넣음으로써 이 문제를 해결하려고 했습니다.  하지만 플레이 테스터들은 이 아이콘을 잘 이해하지 못했습니다.   그래서 스파이의 얼굴에 종이 마스크를 붙여서 구분하게 했더니 게임이 더 유머러스해졌을 뿐만 아니라 플레이어들도 스파이의 얼굴을 잠깐 보는 것만으로도 모든 정보를 바로 알아차리고 자신의 캐릭터와 액션에 집중할 수 있었습니다.  이를 통해, 쉬운 해결 방법이 있더라도 보다 나은 해결책을 찾음으로써 훌륭한 디자인 원칙이 유지될 수 있다는 것을 알았습니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment040.wav"   "[Robin Walker] With nine classes of characters, and so many weapons and unique abilities, one of our biggest challenges was exposing all these combinations to players without overwhelming them.  Even the shortlist of essential information is intimidating, including map goals, the whereabouts of their friends, who's shooting them with what weapon, and so on.  We didn't have any way to make all of this information visual, so first we had to prioritize and come up with an essential list of things every player needed to know in order to just have fun.  Information they could learn by playing the game-such as map layout-was of secondary importance; but there was also information, such as the Medic's invulnerability charge, that would be completely invisible unless we exposed it.  We tried to avoid attaching 2D elements to the HUD as much as possible, since we wanted players to be looking at the 3D world we'd built rather than some abstract representation.  For example, players always see their own team's spies as a spy, but they need to know how the spy is disguised to the other team.  We tried a quick hack where we put an icon representing the spy's current disguise floating above his head.  The icon proved baffling to playtesters.   When we tackled the problem by putting cut-out paper masks on the spy, it not only fit the humorous style of the game, but it let players get all pertinent information directly from a quick look at the spy's model, thus keeping them focused on the characters and on the action of the game.  We took this as a lesson, in how holding ourselves to a strong design principle can often force us to come up with better solutions, than if we'd taken the easy route."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment041.wav"   "[Jason Mitchell] soldier up to here: setpos 281.531250 3295.468750 -124.027405;setang 4.553997 176.268036 0.000000 그래픽 작업 방향에 영향을 준 20세기 초의 상업적 삽화와 어울리는 캐릭터 음영 스타일을 얻기 위해 우리는 캐릭터의 명암 부분을  변경했습니다. 여기 보이는 것은 삽화 느낌의 음영 스타일로 만든 팀 포트리스 2의 솔져입니다. 옆 방에서 나오는 불빛에 따라 솔져의 명암이 어떻게 변하는지 지켜보십시오. 지금처럼 일반적인 명암[set r_identitylightwarp to 1]을 사용할 경우에는 캐릭터 명암이 너무 부드러워 삽화 느낌의 스타일에 맞지 않습니다. 삽화 느낌의 명암 모델[set r_identitylightwarp to 0]에서는 캐릭터의 명암이 전체적인 그래픽 스타일에 훨씬 잘 어울립니다.  back soldier up to here (dark corner near above position): setpos 482.125000 3267.843750 -124.027405;setang -1.386003 -137.399948 0.000000 삽화 느낌의 음영에 있어 또 하나의 특징은 캐릭터의 실루엣 선을 강조하여 배경 그래픽과 혼동되지 않도록 할 수 있다는 것입니다. 윤곽 명암이 없으면[set r_rimlight to 0] 캐릭터와 배경이 겹쳐서 잘 구분되지 않습니다. 윤곽 명암이 있으면[set r_rimlight to 1] 캐릭터가 나머지 그래픽과 대비되어 보이며 팀 포트리스 2의 전체적인 그래픽 스타일과도 더 잘 조화됩니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment041.wav"   "[Jason Mitchell] soldier up to here: setpos 281.531250 3295.468750 -124.027405;setang 4.553997 176.268036 0.000000 To achieve a style of character shading which is consistent with the early 20th Century commercial illustrations that influenced our art direction, we alter the diffuse lighting on characters. Here, we can see the Soldier as he appears in Team Fortress 2, using our illustrative shading style. Note the tight transition between the light and dark sides of the Soldier as he is lit by the light in the next room. Using traditional lighting [set r_identitylightwarp to 1] as seen here, the character lighting appears too soft and does not fit our illustrative style. With the illustrative lighting model [set r_identitylightwarp to 0], our characters are lit in a way which better fits our overall art style.  back soldier up to here (dark corner near above position): setpos 482.125000 3267.843750 -124.027405;setang -1.386003 -137.399948 0.000000 Another facet of illustrative shading is the use of rim highlights to accentuate the silhouettes of characters to keep them from blending into the scenery. Without the rim lighting [set r_rimlight to 0], the character blends into the background. With the rimlighting, [set r_rimlight to 1] characters are visible against the rest of the scene and better fit the art style of Team Fortress 2."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment042.wav"   "[Alden Kroll] 2D HUD 요소는 사용자가 어떤 해상도에서 게임을 실행하더라도 문제없이 보기 좋아야 한다는 특유의 그래픽 문제가 있습니다. 오늘날의 고해상도 와이드스크린 디스플레이를 감안할 때 이를 위해서는 다량의 텍스처 메모리와 여러 가지 디스플레이 해상도를 고려한 다량의 작업이 필요합니다. TF2의 문제는 더욱 복잡했습니다. 우리는 HUD에 부드러운 곡선의 요소를 포함시키고자 했기 때문입니다. 그래서 선형 그래픽 이미지를 그리기 위한 새로운 쉐이더 시스템을 개발했습니다.  이 시스템은 매우 높은 해상도로 확대해도 실루엣이 부드럽게 표현되는 이미지를 고정된 해상도에서 만들 수 있도록 해줍니다. 이 쉐이더 시스템은 윤곽 처리 및 낙하 그림자도 처리할 수 있으며 표지판과 같은 3D 공간의 요소에도 적용될 수 있습니다.  "
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment042.wav"   "[Alden Kroll] Two-dimensional HUD elements present a particular art problem, because they have to look good and sharp no matter what resolution the user is running their game at. Given today's availability of high resolution wide-screen displays, this can require a lot of texture memory and a lot of work anticipating different display resolutions. The problem for TF2 was even more daunting because of our desire to include a lot of smooth curved elements in our HUD. We developed a new shader system for drawing 'line art' images.  The system allows us to create images at a fixed resolution that produced smooth silhouettes even when scaled up to a very high resolution. This shader system also handles outlining and drop-shadows, and can be applied in the 3D space to world elements such as signs.  "
"#commentary\tf2-Comment043.wav"   "[Chris Green] 우리는 다양한 무기 및 클래스 능력을 표현할 수 있는 다수의 특수 입자 효과를 팀 포트리스 2에 구현하고자 했습니다. 이전 버전의 Source 엔진에서는 모든 입자 효과에 대해 프로그래머가 사용자 지정 코드를 작성해야 했습니다. 팀 포트리스 2에서는 디자이너가 새로운 입자 시스템을 쉽게 만들고 프로그래머의 개입 없이도 기존의 시스템을 반복적으로 재활용할 수 있도록 했습니다. 게임 내 편집기를 통해 디자이너는 입자 시스템의 정의를 편집하고 게임 내에서 나타날 효과를 미리 볼 수 있습니다.  또한 그래픽 담당자는 편집기에서 모듈식 효과 '빌딩 블록'을 연결하여 복잡한 시각적 효과를 만들어 낼 수 있습니다. 입자 시스템 자체에 대해서는 다량의 시스템 부담을 그래픽 가속기 쪽으로 넘겨 프레임 속도의 저하 없이 화면에 표시되는 입자 수를 늘릴 수 있었습니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment043.wav"   "[Chris Green] We intended Team Fortress 2 to feature many special particle effects to enhance the wide variety of weapons and class abilities. In previous versions of the Source engine, all particle effects required that custom code be written by the programmers. For Team Fortress 2, we created a system where designers can rapidly create new particle systems and iteratively refine existing ones, without programmer involvement. An in-game editor allows designers to edit the definitions of particle systems and immediately preview effects in the game itself.  The editor also allows artists to connect modular effect 'building blocks' to create complex visual effects. As for the particle system itself, we have offloaded many of the system calculations to the graphics accelerator, which allows us to increase the number of particles onscreen without reducing the framerate."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment044.wav"   "[Eric Kirchmer] 게임 세계 및 캐릭터에 대한 그래픽의 방향을 정한 후에는 무기와 각종 장비 쪽으로 시선을 돌렸습니다. 이러한 물체는 어느 정도 사실에 근거하되 여러 가지 방법으로 변형되었습니다. 예를 들어, 솔져의 로켓탄 발사기는 어깨에 메고 발사하는 바주카포를 근거로 하되 한 번의 재장전으로 네 발의 로켓을 발사할 수 있습니다. 이를 스타일리쉬한 가상 세계에 맞도록 설명하기 위해 우리는 무기를 각각의 캐릭터가 자신에게 맞게 변경 및 조립할 수 있는 맞춤형 하드웨어 조각처럼 디자인했습니다. 게임 내의 기계적인 테마에 맞추어 주요 무기들은 60년대의 제품 디자인 원칙에 따라 디자인했고 보조 무기와 근접전 무기는 각종 악기를 모티브로 삼았습니다. 보조 아이템을 통해 각 캐릭터의 개성을 더욱 돋보이도록 하기 위한 시도였습니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment044.wav"   "[Eric Kirchmer] Once we had a handle on the art direction for our world and characters, we turned our attention to the weapons and gadgets. While these objects have some grounding in reality, they usually diverge in significant ways. For instance, the soldier's rocket launcher fits the general mold of a shoulder mounted rocket launcher, but somehow manages to hold four rockets in a clip. To justify this, and play up our stylized Spy-tech fiction, we designed the weapons to look like customized pieces of hardware, personalized and modified by each character to suit his own ends. In keeping with the industrial theme of the game, we looked to 60's era product design principles for the primary weapons, then focused on musical instruments for secondary and melee weapons, thinking these would reinforce the connection between the secondary items and each character's personality."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment045.wav"   "[Jim Hughes] 격렬한 전투가 벌어지는 지역을 디자인할 때는 복잡하고 혼란스럽지 않게 디자인하기 위해 노력했습니다.  복잡한 지형은 플레이어에게 혼동을 일으켜 적을 추적하기 어렵고 만들고 전투 도중 플레이어의 이동과 조준을 방해합니다. 특히 방 크기가 그 안에서 싸우는 플레이어의 수에 비해 너무 작을 경우 전투가 매우 혼란스러워지는 경향이 있습니다.  우리는 맵의 마지막 부분인 이 지역에서 한동안 자유로운 형태의 전투가 벌어진 후에 최종 승부가 결정되기를 원했습니다.  이를 위해 입구가 여러 개인 넓은 공간을 마련했고 플레이어가 상하로 자유롭게 이동하면서 공격하고 수비할 수 있도록 했습니다. 그리고 플레이어가 갇히는 일 없이 언제든지 자유롭게 이동할 수 있도록 엘리베이터와 사다리 대신 램프를 사용했습니다.  플레이 테스트를 통하여 방 크기, 엄폐물 크기, 입구 크기 등의 다양한 요소를 여러 차례 변경한 끝에 결국 수많은 플레이어가 동시에 싸울 수 있는 최적의 공간을 만들어 냈습니다.  "
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment045.wav"   "[Jim Hughes] When designing areas for high levels of combat, we try to avoid complexity and chaos.  Complex geometry confuses players, making it hard for them to track enemies, and interfering with their movement and aiming during combat. The most chaotic combat tends to occur when the size of the room fails to support the number of players fighting in it.  In this final area of the map, we wanted a freeform battle to rage for some time before anyone could achieve a decisive victory.  To achieve this, we built a wide open area with several entrances, and gave players a variety of attack and defense options at various heights. Rather than depend on elevators and ladders, we relied on ramps, since these allow freedom of movement at all times instead of confining players.  Through playtesting we made many changes to the dimensions of the room, the size of cover elements, and the size of the entrances, thus ensuring the area could accommodate a battle of many players.  "
"#commentary\tf2-Comment046.wav"   "[Aaron Barber] 블루 팀이나 레드 팀에 속하는 지역이 있는 2fort와 Well 같은 TF 맵들과 달리 Hydro의 4개 주요 지역은 두 팀 중 어느 팀이라도 소유할 수 있습니다. 따라서 우리는 바위벽이나 터널 같은 구조물에 적합하면서도 중립적인 색상을 띄는 전체적인 테마가 필요했습니다. 그래서 적갈색 바위, 시원한 파란색 하늘,그리고 주변 지역을 보완하는 중립적인 색상을 활용하는 사막 테마를 선택했습니다. 각 지역의 색상은 서로 다르지만 함께 잘 어울립니다.
"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment046.wav"   "[Aaron Barber] Unlike maps in TF such as 2fort and Well, which have progressively blue and red sides, Hydro's four main arenas can be owned by one team or the other. We needed an overall theme that justified structures like rock walls and tunnels, but which also had a neutral color scheme. We chose a desert theme with a palette of reddish-brown rock, cool blue sky and neutral light colors that complement the surrounding area. The colors of the seperate areas vary slightly but still key together.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment047.wav"   "[Chet Faliszek] 팀 포트리스 2의 아나운서인 매클레인은 오렌지 박스의 모든 게임에서 목소리를 들려주는 유일한 성우입니다.  팀 포트리스 2의 역할을 맡게 하면서 그녀에게 같은 대사를 서로 다른 느낌으로 읽어보도록 했습니다.  목소리는 5번째 시도에서 완성되었습니다. 그녀의 실망적이면서도 약간 화가 난 듯한 목소리는 팀 포트리스의 세계에서 무승부란 모두의 패배나 마찬가지라는 사실을 확실히 깨닫게 해줍니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment047.wav"   "[Chet Faliszek] The announcer for Team Fortress 2, Ellen McLain, has the rare distinction of being the only voice actor to perform in all the products in the Orange box.  For her role in Team Fortress 2, we had Ellen try various reads on the same lines letting her ad-lib different personalities.  On the 5th try, she came up with the winner. Her disappointed and slightly angry evil overlord clearly lets you know, in the world of Team Fortress a tie does not mean everyone wins, but that everyone loses."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment048.wav"   "[Laura Dubuk] 어려운 문제가 발생한 지역입니다. 이곳은 기본적으로 실내이기 때문에 기본 구조를 크게 바꿀 수는 없었습니다. 따라서 전통적 양식의 공간을 만들어 내기 위해 내부 형태에 신경을 써야 했습니다. 기본적으로 이 건물은 커다란 직사각형 창이 달려 있는 사각형 구조이며 중앙에는 이와 대비되는 원형의 발전기가 있습니다. 깊이와 시차를 생성하기 위해 우리는 철도와 케이블 같은 선형 요소를 추가했습니다. 바닥에는 대비되는 명암 값을 이용했고 통로를 이용하여 흥미로운 값 패턴을 만들어 냈습니다. 이 모든 요소가 결합하어 플레이어의 시선을 플래그로 이끕니다. 플래그는 항상 그 지역의 시선이 집중되는 곳에 있어야 하기 때문입니다."
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment048.wav"   "[Laura Dubuk] This area presented a difficult problem. Since the arena is primarily an interior, there wasn't much we could do to alter its basic structure, so we concentrated on careful management of the interior shapes to create an iconic space. The building is essentially a box with big rectangular windows, contrasted by round elements (generators) in the center. To create depth and parallax, we added linear elements such as railings and cables. We used contrasting values of dark and light on the floor, with walkways to create an interesting value pattern. All these elements work together to draw the player's eye to the flag--which must always be the focal point of the arena."
}
}
