"lang" { 
"Language" "japanese" 
"Tokens" 
{
"#commentary\tf2-Comment000.wav"   "[Gabe Newell] Team Fortress 2 へようこそ。 この作品は開発に 9 年を要した。待った甲斐があったと思ってもらえることを願っているよ。 解説を聴くには、吹き出しのアイコンに照準を合わせて「アイテムを使う」キーを押す。 解説を中止するには、吹き出しのアイコンに照準を合わせて「アイテムを使う」キーをもう一度押す。 解説によっては、プレイヤーに何かを見せるためにゲームが制御されてしまう場合がある。 そんなときは、「アイテムを使う」キーを押せば解説を中止できる。  プレイ後の感想をぜひ聞かせてほしい。 感想は、gaben@valvesoftware.com まで。ちなみに僕のお気に入りのクラスはスパイだ。 それじゃ、楽しんでくれ!"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment000.wav"   "[Gabe Newell] Welcome to Team Fortress 2. After nine years in development, hopefully it will have been worth the wait. To listen to a commentary node, put your crosshair over the floating commentary symbol and press your use key. To stop a commentary node, put your crosshair over the rotating node and press the use key again. Some commentary nodes may take control of the game in order to show something to you. In these cases, simply press your use key again to stop the commentary.  Please let me know what you think after you have had a chance to play. I can be reached at gaben@valvesoftware.com, and my favorite class is the spy. Thanks, and have fun!"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment001.wav"   "[Jeremy Stone] マルチプレイヤーゲームでは、プレイヤーが使うコンテンツの大部分は他のプレイヤーによって作り出される。  この効果を高めるために、プレイヤー同士の関係を深める機能を追加したんだ。  
たとえば、倒された側に倒した側のフリーズカムショットを表示して、その厄介な対戦相手のことが記憶に残るようにした。  「強敵」機能も、特定の対戦相手が他の対戦相手に比べて要注意だってことを思い出させてくれる。  その相手に復讐して追加ポイントを獲得するチャンスを与えることで、苦手な相手の克服を促してるんだ。
"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment001.wav"   "[Jeremy Stone] In multiplayer games, the content players consume is largely generated by other players.  To enhance this, we added features designed to promote relationships between players.  
For example, the freeze-cam shot of a player's killer helps the player remember specific, troublesome opponents.  The nemesis feature adds an additional reminder that certain enemies are more significant than others.  It creates a small negative reinforcement loop by giving players an opportunity to score extra points with a revenge kill.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment002.wav"   "[Laura Dubuk] マップには、その先には行けないという境界線が必要だけど、環境を屋内や切り立った峡谷に制限しない限り、境界線があっても、プレイヤーには境界外の到達できないエリアが見えてしまうことがあるの。 HL2 みたいに、もっとリアルなタイトルでは、これらの境界線を、ストーリーに沿って、ビジュアル的に説明しなきゃならない場合が多かったわ。 でも、かなり定型化されている Team Fortress の世界では、極めて人工的な感じがデザインの基本になっているから、こういう説明を単純化したり完全に無視しても、ゲームプレイには影響がなかった。 プレイテストでは、たとえば、何もない広がりへと続くこの低いフェンスによって、フェンスの先は境界線外で、進入しても意味がないというメッセージがうまく伝わることが分かったの。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment002.wav"   "[Laura Dubuk] Maps require impassable boundaries, but unless we restrict the environments to either interior spaces or steep canyons, these boundaries can't always block the player's view of the outlying, unreachable area. In our more realistic titles, like HL2, these boundaries often require fictional and visual explanations. In the heavily stylized Team Fortress world, however, conspicuous artificiality is a core design principle and so we can simplify or altogether ignore these explanations without compromising the player experience. Playtesting showed, for instance, that these low fences leading to an empty expanse successfully conveyed the message that the area beyond the fence is uninteresting and out-of-bounds."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment003.wav"   "[Ariel Diaz] Team Fortress の各クラスは、それぞれが独自の方法で攻撃と防御に貢献する。そして、コントロールポイントは基本的に、プレイヤーの注意を中心的な攻撃活動や防御活動に向けさせる方法なんだ。 それに、プレイヤーをマップ上の別のポイントに引き付けるのにも有効だ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment003.wav"   "[Ariel Diaz] Each of the Team Fortress classes was designed to make a unique contribution to attack and defense, and control points are, fundamentally, methods of focusing players' attention on these core offensive and defensive activities. They're also useful for drawing players to different points of the map."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment004.wav"   "[Jeff Lane] 当初のデザインでは、攻撃側がポイントから撃退されると、ポイント奪取のためにやってきたことが全部失われるようになっていた。 単独で敵のコントロールポイント付近にいるプレイヤーは、そのエリアに敵がいると、コントロールポイントを奪取しようという気になれないことがプレイテストで明らかになったんだ。 しかも、あるチームが最後の 1 つのコントロールポイントの防御に追い込まれると、攻撃チームが優勢でも、時間内に最終ポイントの襲撃に成功しないことがたびたびあった。そのせいでドローに終わるゲームが多すぎたんだ。 そこで、攻撃側がポイントから撃退された後も奪取の進捗が完全に失われないように、奪取の仕組みを変更した。この改良で、当初のデザインの問題が両方とも解決されたよ。
"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment004.wav"   "[Jeff Lane] In our original design, once attackers were cleared off a point, they lost any progress they'd made toward capturing the point. Playtests revealed that lone players near an enemy control point had no incentive to try to capture it if any enemies were in the area. Furthermore, once a team was reduced to defending a single control point, the stronger attacking team was often unable to successfully assault the final point for the full capture period, which caused too many games to end in a stalemate. We changed the capture mechanic so that capture progress persists for a while even after the attackers are cleared off the point, and this improvement fixed both of the problems with the original design.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment005.wav"   "[Jim Hughes] プレイヤーがルートの決定を楽しめるようにするには、プレイヤーの現在のクラスとマップの状態に応じて、マップのルートの効果を変えなきゃならない。 水を配置することで、そのルートをとる代償を大きくすることができるんだ。泳ぐ方が走るよりも遅くなるからね。 スパイは、気付かれずに潜入するためにその代償を払うことが多い。 パイロは、水中では主力武器が役に立たなくなるから水を避ける。 敵の防御が固いときに、防御側を背後から襲おうとする場合は、どのクラスにとっても、水路を通るという代償を払うだけの価値がある。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment005.wav"   "[Jim Hughes] To give players interesting navigation decisions, routes through a map should vary in effectiveness based on the player's current class and the state of the map. Water lets us increase the cost of taking a particular route, because swimming is slower than running. Spies often accept that cost in order to infiltrate undetected. Pyros avoid it because their primary weapon is useless underwater. If the enemy has a strong defense, the increased cost of the water route becomes a worthwhile tradeoff for any class trying to hit the defenders from behind."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment006.wav"   "[Iikka Keranen] スカイボックス内の広大な空間に使われるメモリを節約するために、3D スカイボックスを 1/16 のスケールで作成したんだ。 ということは、Skybox とプレイヤーがいる場所の間を移動する列車の処理がちょっと厄介になる。 実際に、移動する列車にはそれぞれ 2 つのバージョンがあるんだ。実際のゲームプレイ空間用のプレイヤーサイズのものと、スカイボックス側の小さいものだ。 中央の建物の両側にある小さな修理小屋は、2 つの列車を入れ替えるポイントを隠してくれているんだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment006.wav"   "[Iikka Keranen] We build our 3d skyboxes at 1/16th scale to reduce the memory used by the large spaces in them. This means we have to get a little tricky when dealing with trains moving between the skybox and the player space. There are actually two versions of each moving train; A player-scaled one for the actual gameplay space, and a tiny one out in the skybox. The small repair sheds on either side of the middle building disguise the point at which we swap between the two trains."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment007.wav"   "[Andrea Wicklund] 対戦の結果、一方のチームが勝ってもう一方が負けるというのが理想よ。 ドローは実質、どっちのチームにとっても損失なの。 ドローを避けるために、マップのデザインでは 2 つの重要な変数を考慮したわ。チームの復活時間と、復活ポイントから前線への移動時間よ。 勝っているチームは復活時間が少し早まり、復活ポイントも前線に近くなる。優勢なチームが、さらに有利な条件を得るってわけよ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment007.wav"   "[Andrea Wicklund] Ideally, matches should end in a victory for one team and a loss for the other. Stalemates are essentially a loss for both teams. To avoid stalemates, our map design considers two key variables: team respawn times and travel time from the respawn point to the frontline. The team that's winning gets slightly faster respawn times and more forward respawn points, a positive reinforcement loop that increases the chances for them to push forward and win the game."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment008.wav"   "[Dave RIller] スナイパーを考慮すると、マップには広いオープンスペース、長い照準線、身を隠す場所が必要になる。  スナイパーのターゲットには、スナイパーの照準線を回避する別のルートが必要だ。移動時間が増えるとか、その代償は高くつくのが通常だけど。  これによってプレイヤーに選択肢が残される。直接的だけど危険なルートをとるか、安全だが時間のかかるルートをとるか。  また、スナイパーには通常、対応する敵のスナイパーがいて、アリーナ（戦いの舞台）の反対側に陣取っている。だから、一方のスナイパーが他方を迎え撃ち、身を隠す場所のない所で戦っている味方を援護することができるんだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment008.wav"   "[Dave RIller] To accommodate snipers, maps need wide open spaces, long sightlines, and protective cover.  Targets of the Sniper require alternate routes that bypass the Sniper's sightlines, though these usually have an additional cost, such as increased travel time.  This leaves players with a choice:  do they take the more direct, but hazardous route, or the safer yet slower route?  Sniper positions generally also have a corresponding enemy sniper deck, positioned on the other side of the arena, which allows one sniper to counter another, offering cover for teammates in exposed areas."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment009.wav"   "[Bay Raitt] ドローになるのはたいていドアの周辺だ。どのチームもドアの両側で防御を固めているからね。 これに対抗できるように、別のルートを用意したんだ。移動面の代償が大きくて、メインルートの先で敵が防御を固めているときにだけ使いたくなるようなやつをね。 エリアへの敵の侵入ポイントの数は、エリアのデザイン上すごく重要だ。敵が複数の戦線から接近した場合、エリアを守り抜くのはとても困難だからね。 だから、一方通行の出口はデザイン的に便利なんだ。これのおかげで、敵の侵入ポイントの数を味方の攻撃ルートの数と切り離して考えることができるからね。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment009.wav"   "[Bay Raitt] Stalemates generally occur around doors, where teams have a strong defensive presence on either side of the opening. To help counter this, we provide alternate routes with high travel costs that become more attractive only when the enemy has strong defenses behind the main route. The number of enemy entry points into an area is crucial to its design, since it's extremely hard to hold an area when enemies approach from multiple fronts. This makes one way exits a useful design tool, since they let us uncouple the number of enemy entry points from the number of friendly offensive routes."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment010.wav"   "[Jamaal Bradley] ゲームプレイ上の目的のために、時には各クラスのスピードの差が出ないような仕組みを考える必要がある。 たとえば、これらの中央のドアタイマーは、実際の戦闘開始時間までに全クラスがマップの中央部に到達できるようにするために作成されたものだ。 両チームをグループとして待機させておいて、ドアが開くと同時に一気に衝突させた方が面白いってことがプレイテストで分かったんだ。 戦闘開始前のドキドキ感と、危険な移動する列車の相乗効果で、中央のコントロールポイントをめぐる出会い頭の衝突が劇的なものになっているよ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment010.wav"   "[Jamaal Bradley] For gameplay purposes, we sometimes need to neutralize the speeds of the classes. For instance, these central door timers were created to ensure that all classes could make it to the middle part of the map by the time the action actually starts. Playtesting showed that it was more fun to have the teams waiting as a group as soon as the doors open. The anticipation of battle, combined with the hazardous moving trains, creates a great opening clash for the middle control point."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment011.wav"   "[Matt Boone] 防弾ガラスは、コントロールポイント周辺のような防御が固いエリアには便利だ。 攻撃側のチームには、敵の防御体制やセントリーガンの位置が見えるし、防御側のチームには、攻撃側が集結している様子がよく見える。 攻撃側がメディックの不死身チャージを待っている場合は、防御側にとってこの防弾ガラスが重要になることが多いんだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment011.wav"   "[Matt Boone] Bulletproof glass is a useful design tool in strongly defended areas, such as around control points. It gives the offensive team a chance to see enemy defenders and sentrygun positions, while affording the defensive team a good view of the gathering attackers. This is often crucial for the defense if the offense is waiting for a Medic's invulnerability charge."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment012.wav"   "[Matthew Russell] 攻防マップでドローになるときは、劣勢の攻撃チームが無理な戦いに挑み、そのまま時間切れになるというケースが多い。 これを避けるために、負けそうなときは雪だるま式にできるだけ早く実際の負けに発展するような仕組みにしたんだ。 開始時は制限時間が短く、攻撃側のチームがポイントの奪取に成功するたびに時間が追加されていく。 この方法なら、できるだけ短時間でラウンドが展開され、緊迫間がずっと保たれる。 ラウンド時間が長いと、緊迫感を出したくてもうまくいかないんだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment012.wav"   "[Matthew Russell] On Attack/Defend maps, stalemates generally involve a weakly positioned attacking team beating its head against the wall as the timer bleeds out. To avoid this, we encourage likely losses to snowball into actual losses as quickly as possible. We start with a short time limit, and then add time whenever the offensive team succeeds in capturing a point. This way the round plays out in as short a time as possible and keeps the tension high throughout. Long round times aren't conducive to the sense of urgency we want to create."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment013.wav"   "[John Cook] 防御可能な建物をデザインするときは、高さを利用すると便利だ。 たとえば、奪取ポイント B は、全方向から防御する必要がある。 建物内からロケット弾やグレネード（手榴弾）を発射する場合は、この建物内の防御陣にとって高さと四方の窓が利点となる。 一部の窓は防弾ガラスになっていて、敵の接近を安全に見ることができるんだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment013.wav"   "[John Cook] Height is a useful feature when designing defensible buildings. For instance, the Cap B building needs to be defended from all directions. The height, and windows on all sides, give defenders in this building an advantage, when launching rockets & grenades from within. Bulletproof glass in some windows lets them safely view approaching enemies."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment014.wav"   "[Jake Nicholson ] ソルジャーのために、高さには特に注意を払って空間をデザインしたよ。 通常ソルジャーは、ロケットランチャーの爆風によるダメージを最大限に活かすために、敵を上から撃つことを好む。 ここでは屋根の上がそのポイントだ。 それに、ここはソルジャーのロケットジャンプでしかたどり着けない場所でもある。普通は他のクラスが利用することはできないんだ。 ソルジャーは自分のロケットジャンプの爆風によってダメージを受けるから、高さというメリットをヘルスと引き換えにしなくてはならない。 このメリットを、ヘルスの欠乏というデメリットと組み合わせることで、マップのバランスを崩すことなく、屋根を有効なスポットにすることができた。ソルジャーは、ヘルスを維持するために屋根から下りてメディックに頼る必要があるからだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment014.wav"   "[Jake Nicholson ] For Soldiers, we design spaces with specific attention to height. Soldiers generally want to be shooting down at opponents to maximize the effect of their rockets' splash damage. The rooftop here gives them that advantage. It can also only be reached with the soldier's rocket jump, making it generally inaccessible to the other classes. Because of the splash damage from a rocket jump, soldiers have to trade health for the height advantage. This tradeoff, coupled with the lack of health on the roof, lets usmake the rooftop a powerful advantage without unbalancing the map, since soldiers will need to rely on medics down below to keep them healthy."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment015.wav"   "[Dave Riller] スカウトのクラスを考慮すると、マップにオープンスペースが必要なんだ。それがあることで、他のクラスには不可能なルートをスカウトはダブルジャンプで進める。  このエリアにはいろんな屋根や岩がある。スカウトはそれらを渡ることでスカウト以外の敵の頭上を行くことができるんだ。  スカウトはよく、スピードのメリットを活かして逃げ、ヘルスを取り戻す。だからここでは、狭く閉鎖的なエリアにヘルスを配置することで、スカウトが多少のリスクを犯さざるを得ないようにしたんだ。こういう所では移動の自由が制限されるからね。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment015.wav"   "[Dave Riller] To accommodate the scout class, maps need open spaces that allow scouts to double jump along paths that the other classes can't navigate.  This area features a variety of rooftops and rocks that a scout can traverse while staying above any non-scout opponents.  Scouts often use their speed advantage to retreat and collect health, so here we force them to adopt some risk by placing the health inside a small, enclosed area, where they sacrifice some freedom of movement."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment016.wav"   "[Matt Boone] スパイは、敵の裏をかくのが好きなプレイヤーのためにデザインされたんだ。 ハイレベルなプレイヤーなら、敵チームに潜入し、変装して動き回り、敵を即死させることができる背後からの一撃で主な敵（たいていはスナイパー、エンジニア、メディック）を排除する、という流れのプレイになる。 スパイの透明マントは、主に 2 つの状況で役に立つようになっている。 1 つは、前線を通過する場合だ。前線は、敵に対する警戒が一番厳しく、あらぬ方向に向かう味方が最も疑われる場所だ。 2 つ目は、敵陣にいるときに敵に変装を見破られて逃げる場合だ。 スパイのサッパーは、敵のセントリーガンを無人で簡単に破壊できるようにとデザインされた。こいつのおかげで敵のエンジニアは、自分が作った装置に目を光らせてないといけなくなるんだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment016.wav"   "[Matt Boone] The Spy is designed for players who want to outsmart their opponents. At a high level, his gameplay flow is to infiltrate the enemy team, move around while disguised, and use his instant-kill backstab to take out key enemies, usually snipers, engineers, and medics. His invisibility cloak is designed to help him in two key situations. The first is in getting past the frontline, where players are most vigilant against enemies and most suspicious of friends not heading in the right direction. The second is in escaping from enemies who have seen through his disguise while he's in enemy territory. His sapper was designed to allow him to easily take out unattended enemy sentryguns, forcing enemy engineers to keep a close eye on their buildings."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment017.wav"   "[Eric Kirchmer] エンジニアが作る AI 制御のセントリーガンの威力のバランスをとることは、Team Fortress 2 のデザインにおける難問の 1 つだったよ。 セントリーガンが強力すぎると、それに対抗できるのはよっぽど腕の立つプレイヤーだけになってしまう。 弱すぎると、エンジニアは腕の立つプレイヤーに歯が立たない。そもそも、セントリーガンを作る理由が事実上なくなってしまうんだ。 この解決策は、セントリーガンに本質的に 2 つの要素を持たせることだった。つまり、物陰に隠れていない敵には死をもたらすけれども、物陰から出たり隠れたりする敵に対応できるほど賢くないものにしたんだ。 だからエンジニアは、コーナーというセントリーガンの弱点を補うために別の武器の腕を発揮しなきゃならない。単純に傍を駆け抜けようとする敵に対しては、セントリーガンは依然として大きな効果を発揮するけどね。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment017.wav"   "[Eric Kirchmer] Balancing the strength of the Engineer's AI-controlled sentrygun was one of more difficult design problems in Team Fortress 2. If the gun was too powerful, only the most skilled players would be able to counteract it. If the gun was too weak, the Engineer would have no chance against skilled players, effectively eliminating any reason to build it in the first place. Our solution was to make the sentrygun essentially binary in the sense that it's lethal to opponents who don't take cover, but can't intelligently deal with enemies popping in and out of cover. This forces the Engineer to use his own secondary weapons skill to compensate for the sentrygun's corner weakness, while still making the sentrygun a formidable obstacle for any opponent simply attempting to sprint past it."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment018.wav"   "[Andrew Burke] スカウトは、ターゲットを追跡しながらすばやく動き回りたいプレイヤーのためにデザインされた。 他の戦闘クラスが武器に頼るような場面でも、スカウトは、敵の砲火から身をかわすため、移動速度の速さとダブルジャンプの能力に頼る。 スカウトの戦闘スタイルは、主力武器の散弾銃によるところが大きい。 散弾銃は大打撃を与えることができるけど、弾が広く飛び散るんだ。その威力を最大限に発揮するには敵に近付かなければならない。敵に近付けばスカウトが負傷するリスクもかなり大きくなる。 散弾銃は連射できないから、立ち止まって発射し、敵の攻撃をかわして、また立ち止まる、の繰り返しなんだ。だから、その間に敵に殺られる確率も高くなる。 おまけに、散弾銃には小さなクリップが付いていて、リロードに時間がかかる。たいてい、スカウトは戦線から離脱してリロードしなくちゃならない。スカウトのスピードがあれば離脱は簡単だけど、戦線復帰するまでに負傷した敵を逃してしまう可能性があるんだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment018.wav"   "[Andrew Burke] The Scout is designed for players who are able to rapidly move around while tracking their target. Where other combat classes rely on high amounts of damage, the Scout relies on his high movement speed and double jump ability to dodge enemy fire. Much of his combat style is crafted through the features of his primary weapon, the scattergun. It does a large amount of damage, but has a wide spread that forces him to get close to the enemy for full effect, where he's also at highest risk of being hurt. It has a slow rate of fire that encourages him to pause to fire, then dodge, then pause, and so on, which gives enemies a higher chance to hit him at intervals. Finally, it holds a small clip and a slow reload time to encourage the Scout to pull out of combat to reload, something which he can do easily with his speed, and gives injured enemies a chance to run before the Scout returns."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment019.wav"   "[Dhabih Eng] ソルジャーは、中心的な戦闘クラスだ。動きが万能で、遠くからものすごいダメージを与えることができる。 ソルジャーは、ほぼどんな戦闘にも対応できるようになっている。そして遠距離からセントリーガンに対処するという点においては最も優れたクラスだ。 主な弱点は、主力武器のロケットランチャーによるものだ。 ロケットランチャーのクリップは小さいから、ソルジャーはリロード時に注意しなきゃならない。しかも、発射したロケット弾の速度は比較的遅いから、近距離以外では、スカウトのような動きの速い敵には効果がないんだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment019.wav"   "[Dhabih Eng] The Soldier is a core combat class featuring versatile movement and terrific long range damage capability. He's designed to be comfortable in almost any combat situation, and to be the best long-range anti-sentrygun class. His main weaknesses are designed into his primary weapon, the rocket launcher. It has a small clip size, which forces the Soldier to carefully manage his reloads, and it fires relatively slow-moving projectiles, making it ineffectual beyond short range against any opponent who dodges well, like the Scout."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment020.wav"   "[Charlie Brown] スナイパーのスナイパーライフルにも、デザイン上厄介な問題があったよ。 プレイヤーの期待に応えるには、頭部への 1 発で敵を仕留められるようにしなきゃならない。 その一方で、腰の位置からすばやく撃っても同じ効果が得られないようにしないといけない。これができてしまうと、経験豊富なプレイヤーの手にかかったら、ゲームで一番殺傷力の高い短距離武器にもなって、スナイパーの最大の弱点がなくなってしまうからね。 この問題を解決するために、スナイパーのズーム時にだけ表示される、パワーチャージメーターを導入したんだ。 この解決策には思いもよらない良い効果がいくつかあったよ。 
ズームしていないときや、ズームしたばかりのときに銃のパワーを落とすことで、スナイパーがぶっつけの速撃ちでは敵を倒せないようにすることができた。 チャージに時間を要するということは、つまり、ダメージの低いショットを短い間隔で放つか、ダメージの大きいショットを長い間隔で放つか、ということになる。うまく突進すれば、敵にもスナイパーを圧倒するチャンスがあるんだ。 十分にチャージすれば、スナイパーらしく行動できる。そこそこ見晴らしのきくポイントに陣取り、じっくりと狙いを定めて撃つ、ってようにね。
"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment020.wav"   "[Charlie Brown] The sniper rifle was another tricky design problem. To meet players' expectations, a sniper rifle has to be able to kill an opponent with a single shot to the head. On the flip side, we need to ensure it can't be snap fired from the hip with the same effect, because then, in the hands of an experienced player, it also becomes the game's most lethal short range weapon, negating the Sniper's primary weakness. To solve this, we implemented a charging damage meter that only appears when the sniper is zoomed. This solution has several beneficial side effects: 
The low damage both while un-zoomed and at the initial zoom ensures that Snipers can't kill opponents with impromptu snap fire. The charge time means Snipers can deal out low damage shots quickly or highly damaging shots at slow intervals, which allows opponents to overwhelm them with a coordinated rush. The high damage at the end of the charge rewards Sniper-esque behaviors, such as locating a decent vantage point and taking very deliberate shots.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment021.wav"   "[Marc Scaparro] パイロは、接近戦に最適なクラスになっている。待ち伏せというプレイスタイルをプレイヤーに促す狙いだ。 これを実現するために、パイロをオープンスペースに弱くし、プレイヤーが閉鎖的なエリアや出入口付近を探さなければならないようにしたよ。 接近戦でのパイロの優位性に加えて、火炎放射器の効果を見た目に派手なものにした。この視覚効果は、焼き尽くすまでの間、敵を混乱させるのに役立つんだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment021.wav"   "[Marc Scaparro] The Pyro is designed to be the best short-range combat class, aimed at encouraging players to adopt an ambush style of play. To achieve this, we made the Pyro vulnerable in the open, which forces players to seek out enclosed areas and doorways. To add to the Pyro's short range lethality, we made the flamethrower effects visually noisy, which helps disorient opponents long enough for the flames to finish them off."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment022.wav"   "[Wade Schin] デモマンは、最も万能な戦闘クラスだ。激しく攻撃していたかと思うと、さっと切り替えて防御エリアで敵を撃退することができる。 ゲーム内で唯一、間接攻撃の能力を持ち、物陰からセントリーガンを破壊できる。さらに、デモマンの粘着爆弾は、ソルジャーのロケットジャンプに匹敵するグレネードジャンプを可能にする。 粘着爆弾は、デモマンが別の場所にいるときでも、出入口付近で敵の侵入を防いだり、退却を援護したり、コントロールポイントを防御したりできるんだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment022.wav"   "[Wade Schin] The Demoman is the most versatile combat class, capable of rapidly switching from strong offensive pushes to defensive area denial. He has the only indirect fire capability in the game, allowing him to take out sentryguns around the corner, and his sticky bombs give him a grenade jumping ability similar to that of the Soldier's rocket jumps. His sticky bombs can also prevent enemies from moving through doorways, cover a retreat, and defend control points even when the Demoman is somewhere else."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment023.wav"   "[Keith Huggins] ヘビーのミニガンは射界が広いから、すばやく照準を合わせるスキルがないプレイヤーでも、戦闘の真っ只中に加わることができる。 このことで、プレイヤーの照準スキルの価値が低下するから、それを埋め合わせるために他のスキルの重要性を高くした。 たとえば、ミニガンは発射までに時間がかかるし、発射中は移動の速度が落ちるから、プレイヤーは、戦闘の開始と敵の襲来の両方を予測する方法を学ばざるを得ないんだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment023.wav"   "[Keith Huggins] With its wide field of fire, the Heavy's minigun lets players who don't have great twitch-aiming skills still wade into the thick of combat. To make up for this reduction in the value of the player's aiming skill, we amplified the importance of other skills. For instance, the wind-up time before firing and the heavy's reduced speed while firing force players to learn to anticipate both the start of combat and incoming enemy attacks."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment024.wav"   "[John Morello] メディックは、主要なサポートクラスだ。 前作のサポートクラスのデザインにはいろんな問題があった。 防御エリアに引っ込んでいたからあまりスキルがいらなかったし、そのことでゲームで一番面白い部分から締め出されてもいたんだ。 最悪なことに、これは前作のメディックが大して役に立たなかったことを意味する。一番回復を必要としているプレイヤーの近くにいないのが普通だったからだ。 Team Fortress 2 のメディックは、これらの問題を解決するために戦闘の真っ只中に身を置くことを最も重視してデザインしたよ。 さらに、メディックがチームメイトを回復させている間、自分が生き残ることに集中できるように、メディガンをできるだけ使いやすくしたんだ。 実質的に狙いを定める必要がないから、メディックは回復させるターゲットを追うことに集中できるし、ターゲットの方には、メディックという恩人を守る動機が大いにあるのさ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment024.wav"   "[John Morello] The Medic is the main support class. Previous support classes we've designed had a variety of problems. They didn't require much skill, because they stayed back in defended areas, which also kept them out of the funnest parts of the game. Worst of all, this meant they weren't even terribly useful because they generally weren't near the players who most needed to be healed. We designed the Team Fortress 2 Medic to solve these problems, primarily by focusing on keeping them right in the thick of battle. Additionally, we designed the medigun to be as easy to use as possible, so that Medics can focus on survival while healing teammates. Virtually no aiming is required, which lets Medics concentrate on following their heal target, who has a huge incentive to keep his Medic benefactor safe."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment025.wav"   "[Aaron Halifax] メディガンのデザインの目標は、メディックと回復させるターゲットとの絆を深めることだった。  単純にもっと大きなチームを連携させる代わりに、2 人のプレイヤー間に親密な関係を作ることに力を注いだらどうなるか、見てみたかったんだ。  メディガンのデザイン上、メディックとそのターゲットは互いを十分に意識して、ヘルスと相対位置を見守り、慎重に戦術的な選択ができるようになっている。  優れた回復のターゲットとなることにスキルをからめたかったから、メディックがそのスキルのあるターゲットを探し出して密着するようにしたよ。  こんな風に、僕たちが求めていた関係が育まれるのさ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment025.wav"   "[Aaron Halifax] Our main goal in designing the Medigun was to build a strong relationship between the Medic and his healing target.  We wanted to see what we would get if we focused on creating a tight loop between two players, instead of just thinking about getting the larger team to cooperate.  The Medigun's design ensures that the Medic and his target are extremely conscious of each other, watching their health and relative positions, and making tactical choices carefully.  We wanted there to be skill involved in being a good healing target, so that Medics would seek out and latch onto skilled targets.  This helps foster the relationship we were after."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment026.wav"   "[Jakob Jungels] 不死身によって、マルチプレイヤーゲームにテンポの要素が加わる。この要素がないと、よくできたシングルプレイヤーゲームよりも感情の起伏がなくなってしまいがちなんだ。  メディックが仲間に不死身チャージを行うとき、2 人の気分は最高潮に達している。  不死身の効力が消えるまでの 10 秒間だけ持ちこたえればいいとわかっている防御側も盛り上がる。  敵チームが引きこもって自陣から出てこようとしない場合は、不死身になって、ドローに持ち込むための敵の防御をチームが突破できるように助けることでゲームのテンポが良くなるんだ。  防衛の小競り合いがあっても、攻撃側は邪魔されることなく不死身チャージを簡単に行うことができる。  それに、ゲーム上、不死身チャージはメディックの大きな役目であり、ヒーラーとしての腕の見せ所でもある。 負傷したチームメイトを回復させているときの方が、すでにヘルスが十分なプレイヤーのチャージを続けているときよりも追加されるチャージ量が増えるようにすることで、メディックの回復行為を推奨しているんだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment026.wav"   "[Jakob Jungels] Invulnerability adds an element of pacing to the multiplayer experience, which otherwise tends to have fewer emotional highs and lows than a well-crafted single player game.  When an invulnerable Medic & his friend come running in, it's an extreme high point for them.  It's also a rush for the defenders, who know they've just got to hold on for 10 seconds until invulnerability fades.  Invulnerability also sharpens pacing by helping a team push through a defensive stalemate, when the enemy team turtles up and refuses to come out of their base.  Without a lack of defensive skirmishers, it's easier for the offense to build up the invulnerability charge without interruption.  In addition, invulnerability is a great goal for the Medic and rewards him for being an effective healer. We encourage the behavior by adding more charge when the Medic is healing injured teammates than when he's healing ones who are already at full health."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment027.wav"   "[Jeff Lane] マルチプレイヤーのコミュニティには、少数のマップに集中し、それらを繰り返しプレイする傾向がある。  だから、ほとんどプレイされないマップを大量に作成する代わりに、これまでに作成したどんなマップよりも本質的に繰り返し楽しめるマップを 1 つ作ろうと決心したんだ。  ほとんどのマルチプレイヤーマップでは、マップのロードが完了すらしないうちに何をやるかが分かる。  僕らの場合、そのマップの戦闘がどう展開するかは言うまでもなく、スタート地点のような基本的なことですら予測できないマップにしたかったんだ。  だから Hydro は、スタート状態がランダムに選ばれて始まるんだ。  常に変動するテリトリーの占領に重点を置いたから、このマップのプレイが前と似たような感じになることはまずないね。  一方、ラウンド構造が明確だから、チームの集中力は維持されるし、チームがテリトリーを獲得したり失ったりすると、普通に士気が上がったり下がったりするんだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment027.wav"   "[Jeff Lane] Multiplayer communities tend to focus on a small group of maps, playing them over and over again.  Instead of producing a large number of maps, most of which would go un-played, we decided to try and build a single map with more innate replayability than any we'd built before.  With most multiplayer maps, you know what you'll be doing before the map has even finished loading.  In our case, we wanted a map where you couldn't predict even something as basic as your starting point, let alone what you would be doing when you got there.  Hydro therefore begins with a randomized starting state.  The emphasis on control of constantly shifting territories means the map rarely feels repetitive.  Meanwhile, the explicit round structure keeps teams focused, and provides regular highs and lows as the teams gain and lose territory."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment028.wav"   "[Kerry Davis] ゲームでは通常、該当プレイヤーをその他の全員と比較することで、プレイヤーデータを作成する。  でもこれを本当に面白いと思うのは、上位のプレイヤーだけだ。  TF2 では、データをプレイヤーの以前の成功と比較する方がいいと判断して、世界規模の比較システムから、モチベーションが上がる個人比較システムに変えたんだ。 初心者は、スキルはまだ高くないけれども、ずっと上達し続けているという励ましと確信を得られる。 ベテランは、何とか前回の記録に迫ることができたときにそのことが表示されるから、その記録を破ろうという気にさせられる。  個人データシステムは、検証システムとしても機能するんだ。 本当にいいプレイをしたという感触をプレイヤーが得たときは、データシステムがポップアップ表示されて、「そのとおり。すばらしいプレイでした」といったメッセージを受け取るのさ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment028.wav"   "[Kerry Davis] Games usually approach stats by comparing the player to everyone else in the world.  This is only really of interest to those who are near the top.  With TF2 we decided that a better approach might be to compare stats to the player's previous successes, turning them from a worldwide comparative system into a personalized motivational one. The beginning player gets encouragement and acknowledgement that while they're not highly skilled yet, they're getting better all the time. The veterans get to see when they've managed to come close to their previous record, which encourages them beat that record.  The personal stat system also acts as a validation system. When a player feels like they've had a really good run, the stats system pops up and essentially says, 'You're right, that was a great run.'"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment029.wav"   "[Andrea Wicklund] アートの演出で分かりやすいビジュアル表現が多ければ、それだけゲームの要素を説明する作業が少なくてすむ。 TF2 の初期バージョンでは、うんとリアルなアートの演出が行われたの。 時間が経つにつれ、私たちはこれが多くの問題の原因になっていることに気付いたわ。  プレイヤークラス間の違いを存分に出しきれていなかった。  弾丸以外のものを発射する武器は、視覚化が難しかった。  マップは、現実世界ではかなり不自然なものだった。2 つの対立する勢力が互いに 15 メートル以内の距離に基地を築くなんてまずありえないでしょ。  それに、ゲームの見た目ではうちの他の製品と区別がつかなかったし。  でも、この世界を定型化したら、こうした問題がなくなったわ。巨漢のヘビーと、ピンストライプのスーツを着たスパイを比べれば、両クラスの間にはヘルスの違いがあり、ゲームプレイスタイルも全く異なることをプレイヤーは理解する。  プレイテスターは、赤十字のマークがターゲットに向かって流れるのを見て、メディックの回復ビームだと簡単に理解したわ。  定型化されたフィクションでは、なぜチームの基地が隣り合って築かれるのかを簡単に説明できるの。  最後に、TF2 のスクリーンショットは一目でわかるの。うちの他のゲームと見間違う人は誰もいないわ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment029.wav"   "[Andrea Wicklund] The more your art direction can use well-understood visual representations, the less work you have to do to explain your game elements. The earliest version of TF2 had a heavily realistic art direction. As time went on, we found this was causing us a lot of issues.  The differences between our player classes were hard to expose satisfactorily.  Weapons firing anything other than bullets were hard to visualize.  Our maps didn't make a lot of sense in the real world, where two opposing forces rarely build bases within fifty feet of one another.  In addition, the game wasn't visually distinct from our other products.  A stylized world had none of these problems:  Put the massive Heavy next to the pinstripe-suited Spy, and players understand both the numerical health differences between the classes and their very different gameplay styles.  The medic's healing beam was easily understood by playtesters when they saw the floating red plus symbols streaming into the target.  A stylized fiction can easily explain why the team's bases are built right next to each other.  Finally, a TF2 screenshot is easily recognizable, ensuring that no one will confuse it with another of our games."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment030.wav"   "[Moby Francke] 定型化というアートの方向性が定まってから、いろんなスタイルを試して、J.C. Leyendecker を手本にすることに決定した。 Leyendecker は、1900 年代初頭に絶大な人気を誇ったイラストレーターだ。 Leyendecker の衣類や素材の表現は、クラスを見分けるのに重要なすっきりとシャープなシルエット形状を保ちながら、いかにキャラクターの細部を描き込むかの格好の手本となったよ。 衣類のしわは、通常のマップで描いたんだ。間近で見ると、細部まできれいに表示されていたよ。プレイヤーの目を重要な武器に引き付ける色合いを損なうことなくね。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment030.wav"   "[Moby Francke] Having decided on a stylized art direction, we experimented with a variety of styles before settling on the example of J.C. Leyendecker, an enormously popular illustrator of the early 1900s. Leyendecker's rendering of clothing and material provided a great example of how to add detail to a character while keeping the clean, sharp silhouette shapes that were key to our class identification. We used normal maps to craft folds of clothing, which provided a fine level of detail when seen up close, without detracting from color values meant to draw the player's eyes to the all-important weaponry."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment031.wav"   "[Ariel Diaz] キャラクターは、マルチプレイヤーゲームのアートの中で一番重要な部分だから、一番力を入れたよ。  僕たちは、プレイヤーモデルの読み取り階層を作り、プレイヤーがモデルを見るだけで読み取れなければならない情報に優先順位を付けたんだ。  その階層はこうだ。第一に、プレイヤーがどのチームにいるのか、第二に、プレイしているクラスはどれか、第三に、使っている武器は何か。  チームの外観については、各チームにカラーパレット全体を取り入れ、赤チームには暖色を、青チームには寒色を選ぶことで、区別できるようにした。  クラスは、キャラクターのシルエットで区別できるようにした。 独自のシルエットとアニメーションの形状で、遠くからでも、どんな照明レベルでも見分けが付き、モデルのその他の視覚的な細部をどんなに描くよりも効果的なんだ。 最後に、武器はテクスチャで強調した。 プレイヤーの目を引き付ける、コントラストが最も強いエリアでは全部、キャラクターモデルの胸部付近、つまり武器を持つ位置にピントが合わせられている。 さらに、キャラクターの脚付近の暗闇から胸部付近の明るい部分にかけての微妙なグラデーションも、プレイヤーの目を武器に向けさせるのに一役買っているんだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment031.wav"   "[Ariel Diaz] Characters are the most important piece of art in a multiplayer game, so that is where we spent most of our effort.  We developed a read hierarchy for player models, prioritizing the information that players needed to be able to read merely by looking at the model.  Our hierarchy was this: first, what team they're on, second, what class they're playing, and third, what weapon they're wielding.  Team readability was addressed by adopting an overall color palette for each team, picking warm colors for Red and cool colors for Blu.  Class readability was addressed through the character's silhouette. Unique silhouette and animation shapes are more identifiable at far distances, and across a broader range of light levels, than any amount of other visual detail on the model. Finally, the weapon was highlighted through the textures. The areas of highest contrast, which attracts player's eyes, are all focused around the chest area of our character models, right where they hold their weapon. In addition, the subtle gradient from darkness around the character's feet, to the bright areas around the chest, also helps draw the player's eyes to the weapons."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment032.wav"   "[Charlie Brown] プレイヤークラスは、TF2 のゲームプレイの中軸を成しているんだ。 デザイン上、クラスがなぜ便利なのか、理由は山ほどあるよ。 クラスは経験を詰め込んだもので、ゲーム内で他のクラスと比較してユニークになるようにデザインされている。 あるクラスに飽きたプレイヤーは、別のクラスに切り替えて新たな経験ができる。 クラスのおかげで、さまざまなスキルや欲求を持つプレイヤーを満足させることができるんだ。 初心者も上級者も、一緒に楽しめるってこと。 慎重で知的な思想家も、戦略に長けた防御者も、早撃ちのアドレナリンジャンキーも、誰もが自分にふさわしい場所を見つけることができる。 Team Fortress 2 のクラスデザインの決定によって、ゲーム内でプレイヤーができることを増やす一方で、プレイヤー単独の決断は管理可能なレベルに抑えることができた。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment032.wav"   "[Charlie Brown] Player classes form the backbone of TF2's gameplay. There are a bunch of reasons why they're a useful design tool. A class is a bottled up experience, designed to be unique relative to the other classes in the game. A player who is getting tired of one class can switch to another class and get a fresh experience. They allow us to cater to players with a variety of different skills and desires. Beginning and advanced players can have fun together. Cautious cerebral thinkers, strategic defenders, and twitch firing adrenaline junkies can all find their niche. Team Fortress 2's Class design decisions enable us to have a larger number of player abilities in the game, while still keeping a single player's decisions down to a manageable level."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment033.wav"   "[Robin Walker] TF2 を初披露したのは 1999 年の E3（ゲームの国際見本市）で、今は 2007 年だ。 どうしてこれほど時間がかかったかって？  簡単に答えると、納得がいくものを作るためにこんなに時間がかかってしまったんだ。  詳しく説明するには、開発プロセスに目を向けてもらわないといけない。  根底には、何が面白くなるか実際には前もって分からないという前提がある。  過去に面白かったものは分かっている。  でも、3 つのアイデアが候補になった場合、どれが一番面白くなるか断言することはできないんだ。  だから、それを解明する繰り返し可能なプロセスを開発することに専念したんだ。  絶え間ない繰り返しのサイクルに基づいたもので、そのプロセスでは、できるだけ多くの人のゲームプレイを観察することで評価が行われる。  TF2 の開発中は、実に多くの機能を試したよ。最終的に採用されたのはその中のごく少数で、ほとんどはカットされたんだ。  たとえば、初期バージョンの TF2 では、指揮官（つまり戦場をリアルタイム戦略の観点で見ることができる 1 人のプレイヤー）のコンセプトを中心にゲームを組み立てることに重点が置かれていた。  指揮官には、組織を作り、チームに統一的な戦略を提供する責任があった。  でもそこには重大なデザインの課題が含まれていたんだ。  たとえば、指揮官も楽しめて、同時に現場のプレイヤーも確実に楽しめるようなゲームをデザインするにはどうすればいいのか？  プレイヤーと指揮官に他者の働きを重視させるにはどうすればいいのか？  ダメな指揮官に当たった場合や、逆に有能な指揮官がダメチームを率いる場合でもゲームを楽しめるようにするにはどうしたらいいのか？  何ヶ月もかけてこれらの問題やその他の問題に取り組んだけれど、納得できるところまで行かなかった。  おまけに、ゲームがあまりにも複雑になってしまっていた。これは、指揮官の追加を十分に正当化するほど奥が深い戦略レイヤを追加しようとしたせいだ。  結局、ゲームから指揮官をなくすという厳しい決断を下して先に進んだんだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment033.wav"   "[Robin Walker] We first showed TF2 at E3 in 1999, and here we are in 2007. So what took us so long?  The short answer is that it took us this long to make something we were happy with.  The long answer requires a look at our development process.  At its core is the assumption that we don't really know ahead of time what will be fun.  We know what has been fun in the past.  But if we've got 3 ideas on the table, we can't say for sure which one will be the most fun.  So, we've focused on developing a repeatable process that will find out.  It's based on a cycle of constant iteration, where evaluation is done by watching as many people play the game as possible.  In developing TF2, we tried out many, many features-a few of which made it to the final product, but most of which were cut.  For example, our initial versions of TF2 were focused on trying to build a game around the concept of a commander, a single player who had a real-time-strategy view of the battlefield.  He was responsible for building structures and providing a unifying strategy for the team.  But there were significant design challenges involved.  For instance, how do we design the game such that the commander can have fun, and at same time ensure that the players down on the ground can have fun?  How do we ensure that the players & the commander value the output of the other?  How do we ensure that the game is still fun if you have a terrible commander, or conversely, if you're a great commander with a terrible team?  We spent many months working on these and other issues, and never reached a point where we were satisfied.  In addition, our game had become overly complex, due to our attempts to add a strategy layer deep enough to warrant the addition of the commander in the first place.  In the end, we made the hard decision to remove him from the game and moved on."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment034.wav"   "[Kelly Thornton] クリティカルヒットは、テンポを重視した結果生まれた機能の 1 つさ。 クリティカルヒットシステムは、プレイヤーの直前のパフォーマンスに基づいてクリティカルヒットのチャンスを高めることで、ゲームの士気の上下に多少の影響を及ぼそうとするものだ。 要するに、パフォーマンスが良ければ良いほど、成功し続ける可能性が高くなる。 これは、1 人のプレイヤーが暴れ回って立て続けに 3 または 4 キルを挙げるというような、滅多にないハイな瞬間を作り出すのに一役買っているんだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment034.wav"   "[Kelly Thornton] Critical hits are one of the features that resulted from our focus on pacing. The critical hit system attempts to slightly influence the highs and lows of the game, by increasing the chance of a critical hit based upon the player's recent performance. In summary, the better you're doing, the more likely you'll continue to do well. This helps create those rare high moments, where a single player goes on a rampage and gets 3 or 4 kills in rapid succession."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment035.wav"   "[Adrian Finol] Team Fortress Classic と Team Fortress 2 の間の主な変更の 1 つは、手榴弾をなくしたことだ。 
ほとんどのクラスが、よりクラスに密接に結び付けられている補助手榴弾と一緒に、通常の手榴弾を携帯できたんだ。  Team Fortress 2 ではクラス独自の役割を重視したおかげで、通常の手榴弾が一部の主力武器よりも強力な決め手となることに気付かされたよ。  この通常の手榴弾のせいで、戦闘ではどのクラスも変わり映えがしなくなっていたんだ。  さらに、Team Fortress Classic のマップのドローをいくつか調べてみると、手榴弾の乱発が原因になっていることが多かった。 特に問題なのは、次の 2 つのケースだ。出入り口を通過するときに、そこにいるかもしれない敵を無差別に倒そうとして繰り返し手榴弾を投げるプレイヤーと、死の間際にありったけの手榴弾を矢継ぎ早に投げて、自分の死後にキルを稼ごうとするプレイヤーだ。  こうした手榴弾をなくしたとたんに、ゲームがもっと楽しくなったんだ。特に、手榴弾が足元で爆発したときに、なぜ自分が死んだのわからず混乱することが多かった新参のプレイヤーにとってはね。 クラス固有の手榴弾を検証したときも、同様の問題が見つかった。  それらをプレイテストから排除したことで、ゲームをもっと面白くすることにますます意欲的になれたよ。  排除を決定した後、この決定の結果どの機能が失われる可能性があるかを調べるために各クラスを分析したんだ。  特殊な手榴弾タイプを使えなくなったことで面白い決断ができなくなったと判断した場合には、そのクラスに別の機能を追加したりもしたよ。
"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment035.wav"   "[Adrian Finol] One of the main changes between Team Fortress Classic and Team Fortress 2 was the removal of thrown grenades. 
Most classes could carry a standard hand grenade along with a secondary grenade, tied more closely to the class.  Team Fortress 2's focus on unique class roles led us to notice that the standard hand grenade was a more powerful combat decider than some of the primary weapons.  This made the classes more similar in combat-not a desired effect.  In addition, when we looked at some of Team Fortress Classic's map stalemates, they often resulted from large amounts of grenade spam. Two cases were particularly problematic:  That of players throwing grenades repeatedly through doorways, hoping to kill any enemies who might be there, and players on the verge of death throwing all their grenades in rapid succession, hoping to get a kill after they die.  Removing standard hand grenades made the game more fun almost immediately, especially for new players who were often confused as to why they died, when a grenade went off at their feet. When we examined the class-specific grenades, we found similar problems.  Eliminating them from playtests gave us yet another boost in making the game more fun.  Once we'd decided on removal, we analyzed each class to see what capabilities might have been lost as a result of the decision.  In some cases we added other capabilities, where we felt a class had lost the ability to make some interesting decisions, related to its special grenade type.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment036.wav"   "[Hamish McKenzie] プロジェクトの終盤で、ゲームの他の部分が完成しつつあるときに、アニメーションを追加する時間が残っていることに気付いたんだ。  武器固有の「罵倒」アニメーションなどのアイデアがいくつも検討されたよ。  機能を評価するときに、それがどれだけ多くの他の機能に関連しているかを調べたところ、「罵倒」が圧勝だった。  倒した側のフリーズカムにぴったりで、強敵とその犠牲者の間の関係を深めるものだったからね。  「罵倒」アニメーションは、Valve の新しいフェイシャルアニメーションテクノロジを見せ付ける格好の場となったし、プレイヤーがあらゆる角度から検証できるようになっている。 結局、TF2 のキャラクターの個性はさまざまだから、「罵倒」は、アニメーションと声の演技でその個性を表現する完璧な方法だったんだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment036.wav"   "[Hamish McKenzie] Late in the project, while other parts of the game were being finished up, we found ourselves with some time left over for extra animation.  There were several ideas on the table, including weapon-specific taunt animations.  When evaluating a feature, we look at how many other features it connects to, and taunts were the clear winner.  They play well with the killer freeze-cam, adding to the relationship between the nemesis and his victim.  They gave us a highly visible place to show off our new facial animation technology, allowing the player to examine it from all angles. Finally, TF2's characters have a lot of personality, and taunts were the perfect way to show that personality through animation and voice acting."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment037.wav"   "[Eric Smith] Half-Life 2 では、「応答ルール」ってのを開発した。完全に予測することが不可能なゲームイベントに応じてキャラクターのセリフの話し方を微調整できるシステムだ。  Team Fortress 2 では、「応答ルール」を初めてマルチプレイヤー環境に拡張したんだ。  「応答ルール」システムは、単純なテキストファイルにスピーチコンセプトを列挙することで機能する。ゲームの中でテキストファイルに定義されたルールまたは条件に一致すると、ゲームコードによってキャラクターがしゃべる仕組みだ。 たとえば、プレイヤーが武器をリロードすると、リロードに関するセリフを言うのは今だ、という信号が「応答ルール」システムに送られる。 「応答ルール」システムは、ゲーム世界の情勢をチェックし、そのスピーチコンセプトに最適なセリフを決定する一連のルールと照合する。  プレイヤーのヘルスが低下している場合は、完全に良好な状態のときとは違ったリロードのセリフをしゃべるかもしれない。  最後の 20 秒で敵を 3 人以上倒した場合は特別なセリフをしゃべり、水中にいるときは別のセリフをしゃべる、といった具合だ。  会話とルールがスクリプトファイルに保存されているから、ゲームのライターは、コードのサポートを受けることなくゲームにスピーチを追加できるんだ。
"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment037.wav"   "[Eric Smith] For Half-Life 2 we developed something called Response Rules, a system that lets us fine-tune the way characters speak lines of dialog in response to game events that are not completely predictable.  In Team Fortress 2, we extended Response Rules to the multiplayer environment for the first time.  The Response Rule system works by listing speech concepts in a simple text file; the game code then makes characters attempt to speak when the rules or conditions defined in the text file are met in the game. For instance, when a player reloads his weapon, this signals the Response Rule system that now would be an appropriate time to speak a line about reloading. The Response Rule system checks the state of the world, and matches it to a set of rules that determine the best line of dialog to use for that speech concept.  If the player's health is low, he may speak a different reloading line than if he is completely healthy.  He could play a special line if he has killed more than two enemies in the last 20 seconds, another set of lines if he's underwater, and so on.  Keeping dialog and rules in script files gives the game's writers the ability to add speech to the game without needing any code support.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment038.wav"   "[Moby Francke] キャラクターのレンダリングスタイルについては、大多数のトゥーンシェーダーのような極端な方法は使わずに、イラストっぽい、または定型化された外見にしようと当初の議論で決定していた。 シェーディングについては、この種のレンダリングの典型的なものよりもソフトなラインが好みだった。  だから、2D テクスチャを使ってキャラクターの照明を定義し、光と影が交わるポイントでは、色の変わり目で色に勢いを与えるために若干暖かみを加えた。 適切なシェーディングモデルを完成させた後、キャラクターに縁の境界線を追加して、シルエットの縁にいい感じでハイライトがつくようにした。おかげでキャラクターが周囲の 3D 世界から浮き出て見えるんだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment038.wav"   "[Moby Francke] In our early discussions of rendering styles for the characters, we decided we wanted them to have a look that was illustrative or stylized, without going to the extremes of most toon shaders. We wanted softer lines for shading than was typical for this sort of rendering.  So, we used a 2-D texture to define the lighting on the characters, and at the point where light and dark meet, we added a hint of warmth to give it that burst of color at the transition. Once we had achieved the right shading model, we added a rim-term to the characters, so they would have a nice highlight around the edges of their silhouettes, which helps them to stand out from the surrounding 3d world."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment039.wav"   "[Dhabih Eng] パーティクル（粒子）システムの課題は、面白くて視覚的にエキサイティングな効果を作り出すことだった。大げさすぎてゲーム内でその意味が誰にも理解できないようなものになってもいけない。  通常の対戦では、あまりに多くの効果が画面上に同時に表示されるから、一番危険なのは見た目の混乱だ。  だから効果は、すっきりシンプルなものになるよう洗練されたんだ。  ゲームプレイにとって最も重要なものは見やすくなったし、主に見ていて楽しいものは背景に下げることができた。  "
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment039.wav"   "[Dhabih Eng] The challenge of the particle system was to create effects that were fun and visually exciting, without being so 'over the top' that no one could read their meaning in the game.  In a typical match, there are so many effects onscreen at the same time, that the biggest danger is visual clutter.  Therefore, the effects were refined to be cleaner and simpler.  Those that were most important for gameplay were made easier to see, while those that were mainly eye-candy were allowed to fall into the background.  "
"#commentary\tf2-Comment040.wav"   "[Robin Walker] 9 クラスのキャラクターがあり、武器や特殊能力も盛りだくさんだから、最大の課題の 1 つは、混乱させることなく、これらの組み合わせをすべてプレイヤーに知ってもらうことだった。  マップの目的、味方の消息、その武器で撃ってくるのは誰か、など基本的な情報を厳選したリストでさえ、混乱を生じさせる可能性があるからね。  こうした情報をすべて視覚化する方法はなかった。だからまず優先順位を付けて、単純に楽しむためにプレイヤー全員が知る必要があることを基本的なリストにまとめる必要があった。  マップのレイアウトとか、ゲームをプレイすれば分かる情報は二の次だけど、メディックの不死身チャージのように、明確に示さなければ全く見えない情報もある。  プレイヤーには、抽象的な表現よりも僕たちが構築した 3D の世界を見て欲しかったから、HUD に 2D の要素を追加することはできるだけ避けた。  たとえば、プレイヤーは常に自分のチームのスパイをスパイだと思っているけど、スパイがいかに敵チームに変装するのかを知る必要がある。  僕らは試しにちょっと、スパイの現在の変装を表すアイコンをスパイの頭上に表示してみた。  でもこのアイコンは、プレイテスターには訳のわからないものだったんだ。   この問題に対処するために紙を切り抜いたマスクをスパイに付けさせたところ、ゲームのユーモラスなスタイルにぴったりはまったんだ。さらに、それだけじゃなくて、プレイヤーはスパイのモデルをぱっと見ただけですべての関連情報を得ることができ、キャラクターやゲームのアクションに集中し続けることができたんだ。  このことは、教訓になったよ。強力なデザイン原理に忠実に作業することで、楽な方法を選んだ場合よりも、良い解決策を見つけ出さざるを得なくなることがいかに多いかっていうね。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment040.wav"   "[Robin Walker] With nine classes of characters, and so many weapons and unique abilities, one of our biggest challenges was exposing all these combinations to players without overwhelming them.  Even the shortlist of essential information is intimidating, including map goals, the whereabouts of their friends, who's shooting them with what weapon, and so on.  We didn't have any way to make all of this information visual, so first we had to prioritize and come up with an essential list of things every player needed to know in order to just have fun.  Information they could learn by playing the game-such as map layout-was of secondary importance; but there was also information, such as the Medic's invulnerability charge, that would be completely invisible unless we exposed it.  We tried to avoid attaching 2D elements to the HUD as much as possible, since we wanted players to be looking at the 3D world we'd built rather than some abstract representation.  For example, players always see their own team's spies as a spy, but they need to know how the spy is disguised to the other team.  We tried a quick hack where we put an icon representing the spy's current disguise floating above his head.  The icon proved baffling to playtesters.   When we tackled the problem by putting cut-out paper masks on the spy, it not only fit the humorous style of the game, but it let players get all pertinent information directly from a quick look at the spy's model, thus keeping them focused on the characters and on the action of the game.  We took this as a lesson, in how holding ourselves to a strong design principle can often force us to come up with better solutions, than if we'd taken the easy route."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment041.wav"   "[Jason Mitchell] TF2 のアートの演出に影響を与えた 20 世紀初期の広告イラストと一致するキャラクターのシェーディングスタイルを実現するために、キャラクターの拡散照明を変更したよ。 これは、Team Fortress 2 に登場する、イラストっぽいシェーディング スタイルを使ったソルジャーだ。 隣の部屋のライトに照らされているときのソルジャーの明部と暗部の間の絶妙な推移に注目してほしい。 ここに表示されているような従来の照明を使用すると、キャラクターの照明がソフトすぎて、イラストっぽいスタイルには合わない。 キャラクターには、アートスタイル全体に合った方法で光が当たるようになっている。  イラストっぽいシェーディングには、縁のハイライトを使用してキャラクターのシルエットを強調することで、キャラクターが背景に溶け込んでしまうのを防ぐという一面もあるんだ。 逆光照明を使わないと、キャラクターは背景に溶け込んでしまう。 逆光照明を使えば、背景に対してキャラクターが際立ち、Team Fortress 2 のアートスタイルにもぴったり合うんだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment041.wav"   "[Jason Mitchell] soldier up to here: setpos 281.531250 3295.468750 -124.027405;setang 4.553997 176.268036 0.000000 To achieve a style of character shading which is consistent with the early 20th Century commercial illustrations that influenced our art direction, we alter the diffuse lighting on characters. Here, we can see the Soldier as he appears in Team Fortress 2, using our illustrative shading style. Note the tight transition between the light and dark sides of the Soldier as he is lit by the light in the next room. Using traditional lighting [set r_identitylightwarp to 1] as seen here, the character lighting appears too soft and does not fit our illustrative style. With the illustrative lighting model [set r_identitylightwarp to 0], our characters are lit in a way which better fits our overall art style.  back soldier up to here (dark corner near above position): setpos 482.125000 3267.843750 -124.027405;setang -1.386003 -137.399948 0.000000 Another facet of illustrative shading is the use of rim highlights to accentuate the silhouettes of characters to keep them from blending into the scenery. Without the rim lighting [set r_rimlight to 0], the character blends into the background. With the rimlighting, [set r_rimlight to 1] characters are visible against the rest of the scene and better fit the art style of Team Fortress 2."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment042.wav"   "[Alden Kroll] 2D の HUD 要素は、特定のアートの問題を引き起こす。ユーザーがどんな解像度でゲームを実行しているかに関係なく、きれいでシャープに見えなければならないからね。 現在は高解像度のワイドスクリーンディスプレイが入手可能なことを考えると、2D の HUD 要素には、異なるディスプレイ解像度を見越して、大量のテクスチャメモリと膨大な作業が必要になる可能性がある。 TF2 の問題は、さらに手強かった。HUD に滑らかな曲線の要素をたくさん入れたかったからだ。 僕らは、「線画」イメージを描画するための新しいシェーダーシステムを開発した。  このシステムでは、超高解像度に拡大しても滑らかなシルエットを描くイメージを固定解像度で作成することができる。 輪郭やドロップシャドウも処理できるし、3D 空間では標識なんかのゲーム世界の要素にも適用できるんだ。  "
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment042.wav"   "[Alden Kroll] Two-dimensional HUD elements present a particular art problem, because they have to look good and sharp no matter what resolution the user is running their game at. Given today's availability of high resolution wide-screen displays, this can require a lot of texture memory and a lot of work anticipating different display resolutions. The problem for TF2 was even more daunting because of our desire to include a lot of smooth curved elements in our HUD. We developed a new shader system for drawing 'line art' images.  The system allows us to create images at a fixed resolution that produced smooth silhouettes even when scaled up to a very high resolution. This shader system also handles outlining and drop-shadows, and can be applied in the 3D space to world elements such as signs.  "
"#commentary\tf2-Comment043.wav"   "[Chris Green] Team Fortress 2 には、さまざまな武器やクラスの能力を強化する特殊なパーティクル効果をたくさん取り込みたかった。 以前のバージョンの Source エンジンでは、どんなパーティクル効果も、プログラマーがカスタムコードを作成しなくちゃならなかった。 Team Fortress 2 では、プログラマーが介入しなくてもデザイナーが迅速に新しいパーティクルシステムを作成し、既存のものを繰り返し改良できるシステムを作成したんだ。 デザイナーはゲーム内のエディタでパーティクルシステムの定義を編集し、ゲームそのもので効果をすぐにプレビューできる。  このエディタでは、アーティストがモジュール式の効果の「構成ブロック」を結合して複雑なビジュアル効果を作成することもできる。 パーティクルシステムそのものについて言うと、システム計算の多くは、グラフィックアクセラレータにオフロードしたんだ。おかげでフレームレートを落とすことなく画面上のパーティクル数を増やすことができるのさ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment043.wav"   "[Chris Green] We intended Team Fortress 2 to feature many special particle effects to enhance the wide variety of weapons and class abilities. In previous versions of the Source engine, all particle effects required that custom code be written by the programmers. For Team Fortress 2, we created a system where designers can rapidly create new particle systems and iteratively refine existing ones, without programmer involvement. An in-game editor allows designers to edit the definitions of particle systems and immediately preview effects in the game itself.  The editor also allows artists to connect modular effect 'building blocks' to create complex visual effects. As for the particle system itself, we have offloaded many of the system calculations to the graphics accelerator, which allows us to increase the number of particles onscreen without reducing the framerate."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment044.wav"   "[Eric Kirchmer] ゲームの世界とキャラクターのアートの演出を把握した後は、武器や装置に目を向けた。 これらは、一部現実のものを下地にしつつ、たいていは大幅に異なるものになっている。 たとえば、ソルジャーのロケットランチャーは、肩に担ぐ通常型のロケットランチャーだけど、クリップに 4 発装弾することができる。 これを正当化し、TF2 の定型化されたスパイテクフィクションを強調するために、武器のデザインは、各キャラクターが自分の目的に合わせて専用に改良した、カスタマイズ武器に見えるようにしたんだ。 ゲームの産業テーマに沿って、主力武器については 60 年代の製品のデザイン原理に倣った。補助武器および接近戦用武器については楽器に注目したんだけど、これは補助アイテムと各キャラクターの個性との関係が強化されると考えてのことだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment044.wav"   "[Eric Kirchmer] Once we had a handle on the art direction for our world and characters, we turned our attention to the weapons and gadgets. While these objects have some grounding in reality, they usually diverge in significant ways. For instance, the soldier's rocket launcher fits the general mold of a shoulder mounted rocket launcher, but somehow manages to hold four rockets in a clip. To justify this, and play up our stylized Spy-tech fiction, we designed the weapons to look like customized pieces of hardware, personalized and modified by each character to suit his own ends. In keeping with the industrial theme of the game, we looked to 60's era product design principles for the primary weapons, then focused on musical instruments for secondary and melee weapons, thinking these would reinforce the connection between the secondary items and each character's personality."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment045.wav"   "[Jim Hughes] ハイレベルな戦闘を繰り広げるエリアをデザインするときは、複雑さと混乱を避ける努力をしたよ。  複雑なジオメトリはプレイヤーを混乱させ、敵の追跡を困難にするし、戦闘中は動きや照準の妨げになる。 戦闘が最も混乱するのは、部屋が狭くてそこで戦っているプレイヤーを収容しきれないときだ。  マップのこの最終エリアでは、誰かが決定的な勝利を達成するまでしばらくの間、自由形式で激戦が繰り広げられるようにしたかった。  これを実現するために、入口が複数ある広いオープンエリアを構築し、プレイヤーがさまざまな高さで、多様な攻撃方法、防御方法をとれるようにした。 エレベーターやハシゴよりもむしろ、スロープに頼ったのは、プレイヤーを閉じ込めたりせずに常に自由な動きを可能にするからだ。  プレイテストを通して、部屋の寸法、遮蔽物のサイズ、入口のサイズを何度も変更し、大人数の戦闘が可能なエリアに仕上げたんだ。  "
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment045.wav"   "[Jim Hughes] When designing areas for high levels of combat, we try to avoid complexity and chaos.  Complex geometry confuses players, making it hard for them to track enemies, and interfering with their movement and aiming during combat. The most chaotic combat tends to occur when the size of the room fails to support the number of players fighting in it.  In this final area of the map, we wanted a freeform battle to rage for some time before anyone could achieve a decisive victory.  To achieve this, we built a wide open area with several entrances, and gave players a variety of attack and defense options at various heights. Rather than depend on elevators and ladders, we relied on ramps, since these allow freedom of movement at all times instead of confining players.  Through playtesting we made many changes to the dimensions of the room, the size of cover elements, and the size of the entrances, thus ensuring the area could accommodate a battle of many players.  "
"#commentary\tf2-Comment046.wav"   "[Aaron Barber] 青チームと赤チームで徐々にエリアを奪い合う 2fort や Well といった TF のマップとは違って、Hydro の主な 4 つのアリーナは、どちらか一方のチームが所有することになる。 僕らには、岩の壁やトンネルのような構造を正当化しつつも、中間色も配色できる全体的なテーマが必要だった。 選択したのは、赤褐色の岩、涼しげな青空、周囲を引き立たせる明るい中間色、という配色の砂漠のテーマだった。 各エリアの色は若干異っていても、互いに調和しているんだ。
"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment046.wav"   "[Aaron Barber] Unlike maps in TF such as 2fort and Well, which have progressively blue and red sides, Hydro's four main arenas can be owned by one team or the other. We needed an overall theme that justified structures like rock walls and tunnels, but which also had a neutral color scheme. We chose a desert theme with a palette of reddish-brown rock, cool blue sky and neutral light colors that complement the surrounding area. The colors of the seperate areas vary slightly but still key together.
"
"#commentary\tf2-Comment047.wav"   "[Chet Faliszek] Team Fortress 2 のアナウンサー役を務めた Ellen McLain は、稀な存在だ。The Orange Box（オレンジボックス）のすべてのゲームに出演している声優は、彼女だけだからね。  Team Fortress 2 では、Ellen には同じセリフに対していろんな読み方を試してもらった。アドリブを交えて、それぞれ違った個性を出してもらったんだ。  そして、5 回目のトライで、満足のいくものができた。 落胆して、少し怒りも入った、彼女の悪の支配者的な声を聞けば、Team Fortress の世界では、ドローは勝ちではなく、負けを意味するんだということが分かるはずだ。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment047.wav"   "[Chet Faliszek] The announcer for Team Fortress 2, Ellen McLain, has the rare distinction of being the only voice actor to perform in all the products in the Orange box.  For her role in Team Fortress 2, we had Ellen try various reads on the same lines letting her ad-lib different personalities.  On the 5th try, she came up with the winner. Her disappointed and slightly angry evil overlord clearly lets you know, in the world of Team Fortress a tie does not mean everyone wins, but that everyone loses."
"#commentary\tf2-Comment048.wav"   "[Laura Dubuk] このエリアは難問だったわ。 アリーナは主に屋内だから、基本構造を変更するためにできることはあまりなかった。だから屋内の形状を慎重に管理して類型的な空間を作ることに専念したの。 建物は基本的に、大きな長方形の窓を持つ箱で、中央の丸い要素（発電機）と対比されている。 深度と視差を作るために、手すりやケーブルといった線形要素を追加したわ。 通路の床には明暗の対照的な値を使用して、面白い値のパターンを作り出している。 これらの要素がすべて連動して、プレイヤーの目を旗に引き付けるの。この旗が常にアリーナの中心じゃなきゃならないから。"
"[english]#commentary\tf2-Comment048.wav"   "[Laura Dubuk] This area presented a difficult problem. Since the arena is primarily an interior, there wasn't much we could do to alter its basic structure, so we concentrated on careful management of the interior shapes to create an iconic space. The building is essentially a box with big rectangular windows, contrasted by round elements (generators) in the center. To create depth and parallax, we added linear elements such as railings and cables. We used contrasting values of dark and light on the floor, with walkways to create an interesting value pattern. All these elements work together to draw the player's eye to the flag--which must always be the focal point of the arena."
}
}
